<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="116"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[‫ ﺟﺎﻣـﻌـﺔ ﺍﻟﻤﻨﺼـﻮﺭﺓ ﺍﻷﻫﻠﻴـﺔ‬- ‫ﻛﻠﻴـﺔ ﺍﻟﺼﻴــﺪﻟـﺔ‬

FACULTY OF PHARMACY - MANSOURA NATIONAL UNIVERSITY

         FACULTY OF PHARMACY

NEWSLETTER

Under the Patronage of University President

      Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater

        EDITOR-IN-CHIEF                                                     EDITOR
Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh                                       Dr. Bassant Maher

                                                    Vol. 2 - Issue 1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Table of Contents  Chapter I                                                                           10
                   Beyond The Classroom, Real-World Relevance:                                         11
                   Enhancing Learning With Project-Based Activities                                    12
                                                                                                       14
                       Student Activists In Pharmacognosy                                              16
                       Student Activists In Medicinal Plants                                           18
                       Student Activists In Biochemistry                                               20
                       Student Activists In Medical Terminology                                        22
                       Student Activists In Physiology And Pathophysiology                             24
                       Student Activists In Biostatistics                                              26
                       Student Activists In Pharmaceutical Organic Chemistry III                       28
                       Student Activists In Pharmaceutical Organic Chemistry I                         30
                       Student Activists In Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry I
                       Student Activists In Orientation
                       Student Activists In Dosage Form-I
                       Student Activists In Regulation

                   Chapter II                                                                          34
                   Extracurricular Student Activities
                                                                                                       35
                       Enriching Historical Education And Cultivating Patriotism At Mansoura National  36
                       University                                                                      37

                       The First Festival For Student Families And Clubs At Mansoura National          38
                       University                                                                      39
                                                                                                       40
                       MNU Skillverse Club                                                             41
                                                                                                       42
                       Empowering Students Through Resume Writing Skills Workshop At Mansoura
                       National University                                                             43
                                                                                                       44
                       Opening The Door For Participation In The ISF Competition For Gifted,           45
                       Inventive And Genius People

                       Organizing A Workshop Entitled Personal Branding

                       The Welcoming Of New Pharmacy Scientific Association (PSA) Members

                       The World Diabetes Awareness Day

                       Electronic Journalism Covers The Activities Of World Diabetes Day At The
                       Pharmacy Mansoura National University

                       Promoting Antimicrobial Resistance Awareness At Mansoura National University
                       Faculty Of Pharmacy

                       Empowering Students For Responsible Antibiotic Use WAAW 2023

                       Sparking The 1st Community Services To El-Wady School Visit Report

                   Student Wellbeing Hub                                                               50
                                                                                                       51
                   Faculty Mentor Meeting
                                                                                                       52
                   Workshop On Time Management
                   Elevating The Academic Experience: Study Techniques For Semester Exams              53
                   Workshop For Students
                   Enhancing Presentation Skills: “How To Give A Bad Talk” Workshop

                   MNU Pharmacy & Entrepreneurship Pioneering                                          56
                   Global Entrepreneurship Week]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Let’s Unlock The Entrepreneurial Potential Within Our University And Empower           58
                   The Next Wave Of Change Makers. An Entrepreneurial Universities Roundtable!            59
                                                                                                          60
                   Activities Of The First Forum For Qualifying Entrepreneurship Centers Ripple           61
                   Summit

                   Empowering Pharmaceutical Innovators “Entrepreneurship In Pharmacy: Health
                   Care Digitalization” Workshop

                   A Field Trip To Cairo International Technology Fair And Innovation Forum

Table of Contents  Our Faculty New Insights                                                               64
                                                                                                          65
                   The University President’s Commitment To Academic Excellence                           66
                                                                                                          67
                   Scientific Trip To Epico Pharmaceutical Company
                                                                                                          68
                   Let’s Renew Our Energies
                                                                                                          69
                   Celebrating The Selfless Spirit Of Student Volunteers At Pharmacy Mansoura             70
                   National University                                                                    71

                   Unveiling The Unseen: Rare Diseases Exhibition Shines A Light At Pharmacy              71
                   Mansoura National University’s 1st Student Pharmacy Conference                         71
                   Empowering Students Through Academic Advising At Mansoura National
                   University’s Faculty Of Pharmacy

                   Empowering Pharmacy Students Through Educational Pharmacy Training

                   Celebrating The World Future Day At Mansoura National University Faculty Of
                   Pharmacy
                   Fostering Artistic Expression: Mansoura National University Faculty Of
                   Pharmacy Hosts Student Art Exhibition

                   Installation Of E-Stock Pharmacy Software For Pharmacy Management

                   Chapter III                                                                            74
                   Galleries At Mnu Faculty Of Pharmacy                                                   75

                       Pharmacy MNU Organic Chemistry Gallery

                       Pharmacy MNU Physiology And Pathophysiology Gallery

                   Chapter IV                                                                             78
                   Honoring Outstanding Students In Educational Activities
                                                                                                          80
                       Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities Of The
                       Biochemistry Course                                                                82

                       Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities Of The Biostatistics  84
                       Course                                                                             86
                                                                                                          87
                       Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities Of The                88
                       Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry Course

                       Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities Of The Physiology
                       & Pathophysiology Course

                       Let’s Celebrate Our Top Students In The First Semester 2023/2024

                       Let’s Celebrate Our Top Students In The Second Semester 2023/2024

                       Honoring College’s Members, The First Excellence Day

                   Chapter V                                                                              94
                   Meet Our Staff’s Recent Research Publications                                          95

                       Nilotinib Alleviates Paraquat-Induced Hepatic And Pulmonary Injury In Rats Via
                       The Nrf2/Nf-Kb Axis

                       The Clinical Outcomes Of Dapagliflozin In Patients With Acute Heart Failure:
                       A Randomized Controlled Trial (Dapa-Response-AHF)]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Table of Contents  A Multinational Study On The Factors Influencing University Students’ Attitudes  96
                   And Usage Of ChatGPT                                                             97
                                                                                                    98
                   Comparative Novel Green Reversed-Phase High-Performance Liquid                   99
                   Chromatography Method For Simultaneous Determination Of Ivabradine And
                   Carvedilol In Tablets And Human Plasma Using UV And Fluorescence Detectors       100

                   Efficacy Of Montelukast As An Adjuvant Therapy In Rheumatoid Arthritis           101
                   Patients: A Randomized Controlled Study                                          102
                                                                                                    103
                   Evaluation Of Knowledge, Experiences, And Fear Toward Prescribing And            104
                   Dispensing Corticosteroids Among Egyptian Healthcare Professionals: A Cross-
                   Sectional Study                                                                  105
                                                                                                    106
                   Salutary Influence Of Gemifloxacin Mesylate Nanocubosomes Based-In Situ          107
                   Ocular Gel As A Novel Approach For The Management Of Experimental Keratitis      108
                   Induced By Mrsa                                                                  109
                                                                                                    110
                   Investigating Fluorogenic Labelling Of Amine Coupled With Firstorder             111
                   Derivative Spectrofluorimetry As A Versatile Analytical Methodology:             112
                   Application To Estimation Of Benoxinate In Its Eye Drops                         113

                   Formulation Of Lipid Polymer Hybrid Nanoparticles Of The Phytochemical
                   Fisetin And Its In Vivo Assessment Against Severe Acute Pancreatitis

                   Inhibition Of Colorectal Cancer Targets Il-6, Ctla-4, & B7-2 By Tislelizumab:
                   Molecular Docking, Dynamics, & String Proteinprotein Network Analysis

                   Ai-Driven Discovery Of Celecoxib And Dexamethasone For Exploring Their
                   Mode Of Action As Human Interleukin(Il-6) Inhibitors To Treat Covid-19-
                   Induced Cytokine Storm In Humans

                   Bioactivity Of Eriocephalus Africanus Essential Oil Against Concanavalin
                   A-Induced Hepatitis Via Suppressing Immune Cell Infiltration, Inhibiting Tnf-Α/
                   Nf-Κb And Ifn-Γ/Stat1 Signaling Pathways

                   Multi-Targeted Anti-Alzheimer’s Agents: Synthesis, Biological Evaluation, And
                   Molecular Modeling Study Of Some Pyrazolopyridine Hybrids

                   New 2-Alkoxycyanopyridine Derivatives As Inhibitors Of EGFR, HER2, And
                   DHFR: Synthesis, Anticancer Evaluation, And Molecular Modeling Studies

                   Tetraenone A: A New Β-Ionone Derivative From Tetraena Aegyptia

                   Repurposing Synthetic Congeners Of A Natural Product Aurone Unveils A Lead
                   Antitumor Agent Inhibiting Folded P-Loop Conformation Of Met Receptor
                   Tyrosine Kinase

                   Design, Synthesis, And Repurposing Of Rosmarinic Acid-Β-Amino-Α Ketoamide
                   Hybrids As Antileishmanial Agents

                   Design, Synthesis, In Vitro, And In Silico Studies Of New N5 Substituted-
                   Pyrazolo[3,4-D]Pyrimidinone Derivatives As Anticancer Cdk2 Inhibitors

                   Vision, Mision And Strategic Goals

                   Editorial Board]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[President
                Speech

Dear Pharmacy Community,

I am thrilled to announce the launch of the first volume of our pharmacy Newsletter at
Mansoura National University, to share with you the exciting news, achievements and student
participations.
In this 3rd issue of our Newsletter, we represent our commitment to sharing the important
work being done by our staff and students with a wider audience. With each issue, we hope to
showcase the incredible research, teaching, and patient care being done by our students, and
staff.
In this third issue, you will find articles on a range of topics, including updates on groundbreaking
topics, achievements of faculty members and students, and news on upcoming events and
initiatives.
I encourage you to read through this issue and to share it with your colleagues and friends.
By doing so, you are helping to spread awareness of the important work being done by our
pharmacy staff and students to support our mission of excellence in education and research.
Thank you for your continued dedication to the field of pharmacy, and I look forward to the
many exciting accomplishments we will achieve together in the future.

Sincerely,

Prof. Cherif Khater
University President]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Program
                      Director

                 Speech

Dear colleagues,

We are pleased to welcome you all to our faculty Newsletter. As we approach the end of our
second academic year, we are proud to share with you the pronounced accomplishments and
successes of our students, faculty, and staff.
As Editor-in-Chief, I am honored to lead the publication of this Newsletter and provide a
platform for our faculty community to share their stories and achievements. This year, we
have received a record number of submissions, which is a testament to the incredible work and
dedication of our students and faculty.
As Program Director, I want to express my gratitude to our outstanding faculty members who
have gone above and beyond to support our students during these challenging times. Their
commitment to teaching and service has made a positive impact on the lives of our students and
the wider community.
In this Newsletter, you will find articles and updates on our academic programs, community
outreach, and student activities. We hope that you will find these stories inspiring and informative,
and that they will showcase the many achievements of our faculty community.
Once again, thank you for your contributions to this Newsletter, and we look forward to another
successful year ahead.

Sincerely,

Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh
Program Director]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Chapter I

Beyond The Classroom,

Real-World Relevance:
Enhancing Learning With
Project-Based Activities]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Abstract

One of the crucial interests of MNU Faculty
of Pharmacy is providing its students with a
dynamic and immersive educational experience
that bridges the gap between theory and
practice through Project-based Learning (PBL)
techniques. PBL offers students the opportunity
to apply their knowledge, skills, and critical
thinking abilities to real-world scenarios while
honing their creativity, innovation, problem-
solving, teamwork, and communication skills.
This hands-on approach fosters a sense of
ownership and responsibility, as students
actively engage in research, analysis, and
decision-making processes, aiming at preparing
them to become competent and compassionate
pharmacists who can make a meaningful
impact on the well-being of individuals and
communities.]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Chapter I

           Student Activities in Pharmacognosy
                 “In The Hands of Nature”

Encouraging pharmacy students to                 an innovative brand name that reflected the
                                                 quality and efficacy of the drug. Additionally,
incorporate plant scents into medicine           factors such as pricing and internal pamphlets
design and exploring innovative packaging        were taken into consideration.
solutions are essential components of our
mission to cultivate a generation of highly      This activity played a pivotal role in enhancing
qualified pharmacists dedicated to delivering    effective collaboration among students and
exceptional healthcare services. Under the       fostering their ability to convert theoretical
patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, the        concepts into tangible products. Furthermore,
President of the University, and the leadership  it served as a platform for developing their
of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh, the          research skills and nurturing their inclination
Director of the Pharm D Program - Clinical       towards innovation in the field of pharmacy.
Pharmacy at Pharmacy College, along with the
supervision of Assoc. Prof. Yahya Amin and
Assoc. Prof. Amal Fathi, and the mentorship
of the pharmacognocy teaching assistance
staff, the second-level student’s projects were
successfully implemented.

Following the principles of Project-Based
Learning (PBL), the students were divided
into groups who embarked on the initial
step of creating a medicinal syrup infused
with captivating fragrances. Emphasizing
efficiency and effectiveness, the students
focused on delivering a fast-acting medication,
accompanied by a distinctive design and

For more details check the following:

https://www.facebook.com/MansouraNationalUniversity/videos/3523252841295542

10 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

  Student Activities In Medicinal Plants
“Flora Of Mansoura National University”

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif            Examples of Plants Identified
                                                              by Students
Khater, the University President, and the
leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-
Sheakh, along with the supervision of
Assoc. Prof. Yahya Amin and Assoc. Prof.
Amal Fathi, and under the mentorship of the
pharmacognosy teaching assistance staff,
a first-level student at the college initiated
the identification of plants available within
the university’s surroundings using modern
electronic applications.

The students were divided into groups of five
and ensured the accuracy of the information
by conducting online research based on sound
scientific principles, guided by professors
and teaching assistants. The student then
compiled a report on each plant, including
basic information, benefits, available uses,
and the latest scientific research published
about it in specialized scientific journals. This
was done in preparation for creating botanical
identification cards in a dedicated file named
“MNU Flora” as part of the activities of
the Pharmacognosy Department, aiming to
provide real-world training for the student.

This activity is part of the PBL approach,
which emphasizes the value of research and
exploration. It aims to enhance effective
collaboration among students and their ability
to benefit from e-learning and technological
advancements, as well as strengthen their
research skills, information evaluation,
and broaden their research and innovative
orientations in the field of pharmacy.

For more details check the following:

https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=1059954281812237
https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=plant.identification.flower.tree.leaf.identifier.identify.cat.dog.breed.nature
https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=cn.danatech.xingseus&hl=en&gl=US

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Chapter I

                 Student Activities In Biochemistry
  “Genetic Horizons: Unveiling The Future Of Biochemical

                               Discoveries”

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif          graphs, diagrams, images, and texts fostering
                                                 critical thinking skills and encouraged
Khater – University President and the            collaborations among peers. With the
leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-          interactive session that allowed for in-depth
Sheakh, with the supervision of Assoc.           discussions, Q&A sessions, and constructive
Prof. Yousra El-Far, and mentorship of the       feedback, students were encouraged to
biochemistry teaching assistance staff and       distill complex scientific concepts into
as part of the Faculty’s pioneering efforts in   understandable, engaging, and visually
the field of pharmaceutical sciences, and as a   appealing formats.
commitment from the university to develop
its students’ practical and innovative skills
and to motivate them to practice self-learning
utilizing advanced and professional tools, the
students of the second-level designed and
presented posters in the Biochemistry Poster
Day with the aid of BioRender under the
following theme:

“ Genetic Horizons:

Unveiling the Future

of Biochemical Discoveries ”.

BioRender is a web-based tool that allows
the creation of professional scientific figures
for use in presentations, grant applications,
and publications. Millions of scientists use
BioRender to help them save time in creating
such professional figures and graphical
abstracts.

This event served as a platform for students to
present their work in a visually engaging and
informative manner. Students created posters
that represent their research projects using

12 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

More about BioRender:

https://www.biorender.com/

                            Vol. 2 - Issue 1 13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Chapter I

            Student Activities In Medical Terminology
                       “Meditermwiki Project”

Medical terminology plays a crucial role in      terminology wiki.

the healthcare industry, serving as a universal  One of the primary learning goals of the
language that allows effective communication     MediTermWiki project is to deepen students’
among medical professionals, researchers,        comprehension and familiarity with medical
and patients. However, understanding and         terminologies. By delving into the definitions,
navigating medical terminologies can be          explanations, and examples associated with
challenging due to their vastness, complexity,   each term, students expanded their medical
and frequent updates.                            vocabulary and enhanced their understanding
                                                 of the healthcare field. As part of the project,
Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif          students gained hands-on experience in
Khater and the leadership of Assoc. Prof.        utilizing internet tools, specifically Google
Ahmed El-Sheakh, and the supervision of Dr.      Sites, to create an online platform for the
Noha Mansour, with the mentorship of the         medical terminology wiki. This skill is not only
pharmacy practice teaching assistance staff,     enhancing their technical proficiency but also
the MediTermWiki project was successfully        enables them to create educational resources
implemented to first-level students for          and collaborate in future online projects.
developing a comprehensive medical

Sample Of The Wiki Pages Designed By Our Students

14 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Chapter I

     Student Activities in Physiology and Pathophysiology

In discussing the endeavors of our students in the Physiology and Pathophysiology subject, we

implemented a two-fold activity. Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater and leadership of
Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh and Assoc. Prof. Marwa Zaghloul, along with the mentorship
of the pharmacology and toxicology teaching assistance staff, some students were tasked with
crafting models to effectively showcase the physiological and pathophysiological activities of
different organs, while others took on the responsibility of creating posters centered around rare
diseases both besides the theoretical part activity. Each group of students presented their project to
their peers, staff members for feedback and constructive criticism.
This approach holds numerous advantages, serving to deepen comprehension and activity engage
students in the learning process. The multifaceted nature of these tasks not only enhances their
understanding but also fosters the development of creative, teamwork, and communication
skills. The impact on our students is significant, as this hands-on methodology not only solidifies
theoretical knowledge but also cultivates practical application skills, better preparing them for the
academic and professional challenges that lie ahead.

16 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Chapter I

                  Student Activities In Biostatistics
      “Discovering The Art Of Biostatistics In Research”

In light of the crucial role of biostatistics       understanding of biostatistics but also honed
                                                    their critical thinking, exploration, and research
in healthcare decision-making and the               skills, preparing them for future challenges.
enhancement of public health, we are pleased        The objectives of the activity encompassed
to report the successful implementation of the      fostering teamwork and collaboration,
biostatistics students’ activity. This initiative,  cultivating the ability to comprehend and
driven by our commitment to developing              analyze scientific research, applying learned
teaching methods and equipping students             concepts to practical research scenarios, and
with professional skills beyond the academic        enhancing presentation, communication, and
curriculum, was carried out under the esteemed      scientific research skills. Additionally, the
patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, and           activity aimed to encourage creativity and
the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-         innovation, as evidenced by the diverse and
Sheakh. It was supervised by Dr. Bassant            unique designs of PowerPoint presentations
Maher, Dr. Ahmed Hassan, Dr. Kareem Saad,           created by the participating students.
and Dr. Abdelrahman Emara.

The primary focus of the activity was to apply
the knowledge acquired in the biostatistics
course to real-world research papers. Students
engaged in reading, interpreting, navigating,
and presenting internationally published
research papers, thereby demonstrating a
remarkable level of commitment, dedication,
and enthusiasm. The activity incorporated
two parts for all first-level student; part 1 of
reading, understanding, presenting published
research articles, and the second one is to
appraise and find answers for biostatical and
results’ sections for research articles with open
book assessment techniques.

This endeavor not only enriched their

18 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Chapter I

                          Student Activities In
              Pharmaceutical Organic Chemistry III

Organic synthesis involves the intentional

creation of organic compounds through
various chemical reactions and methodologies,
aiming to generate specific molecular
structures. Following synthesis, rigorous
analysis through techniques like spectroscopy,
chromatography, and other analytical tools is
employed. These methods help elucidate the
compound’s structure, confirm its purity, and
understand its chemical properties.

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif
Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof.
Ahmed R. El-Sheakh, and the supervision of
Prof. Khalid Bashir Selim, and mentorship of
pharmaceutical organic chemistry teaching
assistant staff, the second-level students at the
Organic Chemistry department were engaged
in designing posters and presentations that
illustrate their research projects regarding the
structures, synthesis, and reactions of diverse
heterocyclic compounds.

These activities provided a platform for
the students to delve into the basic aspects
of structure elucidation for simple organic
compounds. They learned how to analyze
spectroscopic data of various organic
compounds, honing their skills in interpreting
the information provided by techniques such as
infrared spectroscopy (IR), nuclear magnetic
resonance (NMR), and mass spectrometry
(MS) for structures determination. By distilling
complex information into understandable and
visually appealing formats, students were able
to effectively communicate their findings
to a broader audience. This event not only
celebrated the students’ achievements but also
nurtured their presentation and communication
skills, equipping the students with crucial
knowledge and skills for their future endeavors
in the field of organic chemistry.

20 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Chapter I

  Student Activities In Pharmaceutical Organic Chemistry I
                            “Chemistry Day”

Chemistry is the dynamics of life. Converting the solid data to creative three dimensional projects

by Mansoura National University – Pharmacy first-level Students has been done under the
patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh, with
the supervision of Assoc. Prof. Samar Samir and mentorship of pharmaceutical organic chemistry
staff.
As students benefit greatly from learning-related activities both immediately and over time, activities
have been divided into three main types: 3D Model, presentation, and poster. Students were taught
to search, collect information and create 3D models of different topics of the curriculum.
Finally they are able to present what they know and learn.

22 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Chapter I

Student Activities In Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry I
                              “Speak Easy”

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R.

El-Sheakh, and the supervision of Prof. Jenny Nasr, Dr. Heba Samir, with the mentorship of the
pharmaceutical analytical chemistry teaching assistance staff, a remarkable activity entitled: Speak
Easy was organized for the first-level students. The activity focused on students’ exploration of
various topics in pharmaceutical analytical chemistry through oral presentations and the creation
of informative posters. It was designed to promote teamwork, research, content creation, and
presentation skills and speaking easily.
The students exhibited an exceptional level of commitment, dedication, and enthusiasm. These
presentations were not only demonstrations of academic knowledge; they were a display of deep
understanding, enriched by the inclusion of visual aids and practical examples. Furthermore, the
creation of posters was an opportunity for our students to exceed traditional learning limits. These
visual representations condensed complex information into concise formats.
The activity aligns with the Faculty of Pharmacy’s vision to provide qualified and distinguished
graduates who are able to compete in the pharmaceutical sciences and keep pace with updates
in pharmaceutical sciences. Specifically, the activity promoted innovation, critical thinking,
sustainability, and digitalization.

24 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Chapter I

           Student Activities In Pharmacy Orientation
It is important for all pharmacy students to know the classification of medications, interpretation

of prescriptions and medication orders, general dispensing procedure and factors affecting drug
dosage, different dosage forms and various routes of administration.
Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-
Sheakh, with the supervision of Dr. Ghada El-Emam, Dr. Walaa Ebrahim, and the mentorship
of the pharmaceutics teaching assistance staff, first-level students were equipped to perform an
activity aimed at orienting them to the different aspects of pharmacy profession and development
of pharmacy and to the expressions commonly used in pharmacy practice added to recognizing
different pharmaceutical dosage forms and routes of drug administration.
Students were encouraged to select a drug with the aid of its monograph, they were advised to
design a briefed card and present the data inside at the faculty’s Educational Pharmacy.

26 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Chapter I

                Student Activities In Dosage Form-I
          “Medimix Symposium Dosage Formulation”

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif          for the labor market, increase awareness
                                                 of pharmaceutical manufacturing, provide
Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof.       research, communication, negotiation, critical
Ahmed R. El-Sheakh, with the supervision of      thinking, and teamwork skills.
Dr. Ghada El-Emam, Dr. Walaa Ebrahim, and
the mentorship of the pharmaceutics teaching     The activity emphasized the importance of
assistance staff, second-level students were     pharmaceutical manufacturing in treating
prepared for peer to peer learning activity for  diseases and providing medicine, preparing
formulating and designing liquid dosage form.    students for work in pharmaceutical factories.
                                                 Critical thinking, research skills, and
Each pharmaceutical preparation was              communication skills, which are crucial for
distributed to each group and they were          success in academic and professional fields,
explained how to search and manufacture each     are also tackled.
preparation. The activity aimed to develop
students’ cognitive abilities and prepare them

28 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Chapter I

           Student Activities In Regulation
                   “FDA Expedition”

The US Food and Drug Administration               showcasing the FDA’s effective role. The
                                                  simulation activity also allowed students to
(FDA) is an agency within the Department          learn about the different steps involved in
of Health and Human Services of the United        drug registration and qualification for the
States. It is responsible for protecting and      labor market. This contributes to the creation
promoting public health by regulating and         of a skilled generation capable of participating
monitoring various products, including            in various aspects of working life. Students
food safety, tobacco products, nutritional        are provided with opportunities to participate
supplements, prescription drugs, over-the-        effectively, demonstrate their creative energies
counter drugs, vaccines, biopharmaceuticals,      and excellence, increase their awareness of
blood transfusions, radiation-emitting medical    international institutions, and develop skills
devices, veterinary products, and cosmetics.      such as research, communication, negotiation,
                                                  critical thinking, and teamwork.
The FDA is composed of numerous offices that
provide various services to ensure the quality
of healthcare. The objective of our activity
organized is to enhance students’ awareness of
the FDA’s effective role in ensuring healthcare
quality. Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif
Khater, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof.
Ahmed R. El-Sheakh, with the supervision
of Dr. Ghada El-Emam, Dr. Walaa Ebrahim,
and the mentorship of the pharmaceutics
teaching assistance staff, second-level
students performed an amazing role play
for the roles of the FDA’s offices through a
simulation activity. This practical experience
aimed to support a culture of learning and
develop students’ cognitive abilities by

30 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Beyond the Classroom

       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Chapter II

Extracurricular

Student Activities]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Chapter II

          Enriching Historical Education And Cultivating
             Patriotism At Mansoura National University

In an effort to enrich historical education and foster a deeper understanding of the significance of

the glorious October 6th victories and their impact on Egypt and the region, Mansoura National
University has undertaken an initiative under the esteemed patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater,
the University President. This endeavor is being spearheaded by the leadership of Mr. Mohamed
Abdel Latif – General Supervisor of the Education and Student Sector and Assoc. Prof. Ahmed
R. Al-Sheikh – Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the Faculty of Pharmacy
and the Academic Supervisor of Student Activities at the University, with the supervision of Mr.
Hassan Abu Al-Wafa – Student Activities supervisor at the University, the Student Activities
Sector, in collaboration with the University Students Union, has organized a series of events
to achieve this goal. The university hosted a symposium commemorating the memory of the
mothers of the glorious October War. The event was attended by distinguished guests, including
Prof. Mohamed Atwa, the Dean of the Faculty of Economics and Administrative Sciences, Prof.
Raefa Allam, the Dean of the College of Nursing, Prof. Dr. Amira Taman, the Director of the
Medicine and Surgery Program at the College of Medicine, Prof. Noha Al-Wasifi, the Director
of the Oral and Dental Medicine and Surgery Program at the College of Dentistry, and Prof. Ihab
Abdel Hay, the Director of Programs at the College of Engineering.
The symposium began with the national anthem, followed by recitations from the Holy Quran,
and the screening of documentaries highlighting the historic achievements of the October War.
The event aimed to provide university students with a deeper understanding of this crucial period
in Egypt’s history, which witnessed the unwavering determination of the Egyptian people to
defend their land and restore their rights.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/gCy8CiUAikQLt34W/?mibextid=oFDknk

34 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Student Activities

       The First Festival For Student Families And Clubs At
                      Mansoura National University

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater - President of the University, and the leadership

of Mr. Mohamed Abdel Latif – General Supervisor of the Education and Student Sector and
Assoc. Prof. Ahmed Al-Sheikh – Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the
faculty of Pharmacy and the Academic Supervisor of Student Activities at the University, with
the supervision of Mr. Hassan Abu Al-Wafa – Student Activities supervisor at the University,
the Student Activities sector, in cooperation with the University Students Union, implemented
Clubs Day, where the following teams participated: PMD, Raise, Skill Verse club, MAZAL, Esa.
Each team presented its goals and activities that took place during the past year, explained each
committee within the team, and registered new members. Many souvenirs were also distributed.
The administration of the Faculty of Pharmacy extends its warmest congratulations to the PMD
team on winning the best team in the first festival for student clubs and families at Mansoura
National University.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/MCKEpQcpQi9pwMrW/?mibextid=oFDknk

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Chapter II

                            MNU Skillverse Club

In order to deepen the communication ties between all employees of Mansoura University, and

to support an integrated university environment, and under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif
Khater - President of the University, and the leadership of Mr. Mohamed Abdel Latif – General
Supervisor of the Education and Student Sector and Assoc. Prof. Ahmed Al-Sheikh – Director of
the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the faculty of Pharmacy and the Academic Supervisor
of Student Activities at the University, with the supervision of Mr. Hassan Abu Al-Wafa –
Student Activities supervisor at the University, the Student Activities sector, pharmacy students
SkillVerse’s members shared their colleagues SKILLVERSE Club in the This morning, Sunday,
December 3, organizing a comprehensive entertainment day within the College of Dentistry,
with the generous hospitality of. Prof. Noha Al-Wasifi - Director of the Oral and Dental Medicine
and Surgery Program at the College of Dentistry. The party began with a group breakfast for
the team members, which gave the opportunity for social interaction and strengthen friendship
bonds between them, many interactive and entertaining events and games were organized with
the aim of motivating the participating team members and providing opportunities to develop
their skills and build an atmosphere of understanding and cooperation within the team. These
events come within the framework of the university’s keenness to enhance the positive university
environment and encourage effective communication among all university employees.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=321074814059608&set=pcb.321075244059565

36 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Student Activities

      Empowering Students Through Resume Writing Skills
             Workshop At Mansoura National University

Recognizing the importance of equipping pharmacy students with the necessary skills to succeed

in the competitive job market, the pharmacy student members at PMD team at Mansoura National
University organized with their PMD colleagues a comprehensive workshop focusing on resume
writing. This strategic initiative underscored the institution’s commitment to providing its
students with the tools and guidance they need to effectively showcase their qualifications and
achieve their career aspirations.
The resume writing skills workshop was designed to address the common challenges and best
practices in crafting a compelling and impactful resume. The interactive session covered a wide
range of topics, including resume formatting, content optimization, and the strategic inclusion
of key achievements, skills, and relevant experiences. Students were provided with hands-on
guidance and feedback, allowing them to refine their resumes and enhance their job search
strategies. By empowering the students with these essential resume writing skills, the Faculty
of Pharmacy ensured that its graduates would be well-positioned to stand out among their peers
and secure their desired career opportunities, whether in the pharmaceutical industry, healthcare
institutions, or the broader realm of healthcare management and administration.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Chapter II

           Opening The Door For Participation In The ISF
       Competition For Gifted, Inventive And Genius People

On Monday, the sixth of November, 2023, and within the framework of the vision and directives of

His Excellency President Abdel Fattah El-Sisi – President of the Republic, regarding discovering
talented, brilliant, and creative people in universities, refining their skills, highlighting their
abilities, developing their potential and talents, and developing their spirit of creativity, and
under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater – President of the University, and the leadership
of Mr. Mohamed Abdel Latif – General Supervisor of the Education and Student Sector and
Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh – Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the
faculty of Pharmacy and the Academic Supervisor of Student Activities at the University, with
the supervision of Mr. Hassan Abu Al-Wafa – Student Activities supervisor at the University,
the University’s Student Activities department has opened the door for talented, brilliant and
innovative university students in one of the following fields:

       • Artistic talents
       • Scientific geniuses.
       • Technological innovations
       • Digital talent.
       • Literary talents.
       • Sports talent.
Participation in the Innovators Support Fund (ISF) Competition.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/xAbaTLcBbTYpzjWB/?mibextid=qi2Omg

38 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Student Activities

        Organizing A Workshop Entitled Personal Branding

On Tuesday, 7th November, 2023, The College of Pharmacy MNU and the PMD team held a

workshop entitled “Personal Branding” presented by Dr. Ahmed Awara, Founder & CMO of
ZAD Pharmacy, Business Developer at ZAD Nature Freelance Career Development trainer “Soft
& Business skills Mainly “, Linkedin Growth Consultant Personal Branding Guide & Trainer.
This workshop was under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, President of the University,
and was led by Mr. Mohamed Abdel Latif - General Supervisor of the Education and Student
Sector and Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh – Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy
Program at the Faculty of Pharmacy and the Academic Supervisor of Student Activities at the
University, with the supervision of Mr. Hassan Abu Al-Wafa – Student Activities supervisor at
the University.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/ZqiN3jZ3VuT5be4e/?mibextid=qi2Omg
https://www.instagram.com/p/CzZMwVCtwrQ/?igsh=dWlqajh0ZXkzaXF1

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Chapter II

     The Welcoming Of New Pharmacy Scientific Association
                               (PSA) Members

Under the esteemed leadership and supervision of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, the University

President, the Faculty of Pharmacy has proudly welcomed the newest members of its Pharmacy
Scientific Association (PSA) on Thursday, November 9th, 2023.
Spearheading this event were Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh, the Director of the PharmD
Clinical Pharmacy Program, along with Dr. Basant Maher, the PSA Coordinator, and Dr.
Abdelrahman Emara. These dedicated faculty members and administrative staff have worked
tirelessly to ensure that the first and second-year pharmacy students receive a warm and supportive
introduction to the dynamic community of the University’s PSA.
The event provided an invaluable opportunity for the new students to connect with their peers,
setting the stage for a transformative educational journey. The university’s commitment to
fostering a vibrant, collaborative, and student-centric environment was on full display, as the
new PSA students were welcomed with open arms and encouraged to embrace the countless
opportunities for growth and development that await them.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/100085446049506/videos/830263968850882

40 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Student Activities

                   The World Diabetes Awareness Day

On the occasion of World Diabetes Day, and in line with the values of solidarity and care, PSA

with other MNU Pharmacy students organized an awareness day about diabetes. The Pharmacy
College, under the patronage of the university president and the leadership of the Pharmacy
program director, aimed to increase awareness about this common disease in Egyptian society.
Various activities and workshops were organized to explain how to deal with diabetes, emphasize
the importance of prevention and care for diabetic patients, raise awareness about the risks and
effects of diabetes, clarify the daily challenges they face, and motivate students and coworkers
to adopt healthy initiatives and an active lifestyle to prevent this chronic disease.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Chapter II

   Electronic Journalism Covers The Activities Of World Diabetes
          Day At The Pharmacy Mansoura National University

    Reference:

     https://www.facebook.com/share/p/KFykjzUv8uB8QKPM/?mibextid=xfxF2i
     https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=303788792479320&set=a.108292155362319
     Real: https://www.facebook.com/reel/1061512698217411?mibextid=rS40aB7S9Ucbxw6v

42 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Student Activities

         Promoting Antimicrobial Resistance Awareness At
        Mansoura National University Faculty Of Pharmacy

As a leading institution in the field of pharmaceutical education, Mansoura National University’s

Faculty of Pharmacy plays a crucial role in raising awareness about critical global health issues.
One such initiative was the active participation of the Pharmacy Scientific Association (PSA)
and other faculty students in the World Antimicrobial Resistance Awareness Week (WAAW)
2023.
The World Antimicrobial Resistance Awareness Week is an annual global campaign organized
by the World Health Organization (WHO) to promote the responsible use of antimicrobials and
to educate the public about the growing threat of antimicrobial resistance (AMR). Recognizing
the significance of this global effort, the PSA at Mansoura National University took the lead in
spearheading a comprehensive awareness campaign during WAAW 2023.
The PSA students launched a robust social media campaign, utilizing various platforms to
disseminate informative posts and graphics highlighting the importance of antimicrobial
stewardship. These awareness posts addressed topics such as the role of antibiotics, the dangers
of misuse and overuse, and the steps individuals can take to prevent the spread of drug-resistant
infections. By leveraging their digital presence, the PSA successfully reached a wide audience,
including fellow students, faculty members, and the broader university community.
Furthermore, the PSA and other faculty students organized a series of engaging on-campus
activities to further amplify the WAAW 2023 message. These events included interactive
informative presentations and interviews within the university. Through these hands-on initiatives,
students were able to directly engage with their peers, fostering discussions, answering questions,
and providing practical advice on promoting responsible antimicrobial use. This multifaceted
approach not only raised awareness but also empowered the university community to become
active participants in the fight against antimicrobial resistance.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=306760805515452&set=a.108292155362319
https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=306221088902757&id=100085446049506
https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=308311235360409&set=a.108292155362319

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Chapter II

       Empowering Students for Responsible Antibiotic Use
                                 WAAW 2023

Recognizing the critical importance of antimicrobial stewardship, the Faculty of Pharmacy at

Mansoura National University took a proactive approach in empowering its students during
the World Antimicrobial Resistance Awareness Week (WAAW) 2023. Beyond the student-led
awareness campaigns, the faculty played a pivotal role in organizing specialized workshop
to equip the next generation of pharmacists with the knowledge and skills needed to promote
responsible antibiotic use.
The workshops delved deep into the complex issue of antimicrobial resistance, providing
students with a comprehensive understanding of the underlying causes, the global impact, and
the potential solutions. Through interactive presentations, case studies, and hands-on activities,
students were able to explore the role of healthcare professionals, including pharmacists, in
addressing this growing public health challenge. The workshop emphasized the importance of
evidence-based prescribing practices, patient education, and the implementation of antimicrobial
stewardship programs – key strategies that the Faculty of Pharmacy is committed to instilling in
its students. By equipping the next generation of pharmacists with the knowledge and skills to
effectively manage and monitor antibiotic use, the faculty is playing a pivotal role in empowering
its students to become champions of antimicrobial stewardship, poised to make a lasting impact
in their communities and the healthcare industry as a whole.

44 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Student Activities

Sparking The 1st Community Services To
       El-Wady School Visit Report

Community engagement of universities              which is First Aid Kit, to enhance medical
                                                  knowledge and the initial measures that must
plays an important role in enhancing              be taken when exposed to something that
communication and interaction between the         requires medical intervention.
university and the local community. In order
to enhance health knowledge and awareness         Faculty of Dentistry: Awareness speaker
among children, clarify what a home pharmacy      students from the College of Oral and Dental
should include, and how to take care of dental    Medicine and Surgery organized more than
health, and under the patronage of Prof. Dr.      one presentation discussing the importance
Cherif Khater, President of the Mansoura          of oral care and ways to maintain oral and
National University, and supervision of Prof.     dental health. As tooth decay is considered
Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh, Director of the Pharma        the most common among children in the
D - Clinical Pharmacy Program at the College      age group between 4 and 12 years old, a
of Pharmacy, and Prof. Noha El-Wassefy,           special presentation was organized to attract
Director of the Oral and Dental Medicine and      attention to the importance of maintaining
Surgery Program at the College of Dentistry,      dental health from the risk of decay, and to
and Dr. Bassant Maher - Clinical Pharmacy         know the causes and stages of its occurrence.
department, Pharmacy Scientific Association       Then move on to discussing another program
coordinator - in cooperation with Dr. Noha        under the title Tooth brushing that includes
Mousa, director of EL-wady Language               methods which are preferable to follow to
School, a community visit was made to El-         avoid the risk of cavities and many unhealthy
Wadi Language School on November 23rd,            habits, added to what may happen in the case
2023, to achieve the university’s goal of         of carelessness in oral care with a strong
enabling children to understand suitable          warning about the necessity of visiting the
healthy habits and dealing with first aid         dentist to conduct routine examinations
techniques that must be taken when exposed        on an ongoing basis. In addition, another
to situations that require medical intervention.  program was introduced that sheds light
                                                  on the different types of healthy foods that
The Visit Program:                                support the strength of gums and teeth, such
                                                  as: dairy derivatives rich in calcium, which
Faculty of Pharmacy Program: Awareness            is beneficial for bones and teeth, fresh fruits
speaker students from the Faculty of              and unpeeled vegetables, and water and fruit
Pharmacy, under the supervision of Dr.            juices.
Randa Hani and Dr. Amged Salem, made a
presentation under the title “Home Pharmacy”      The school’s management and staff
explaining the importance of the home             expressed their appreciation for this visit,
pharmacy and what it should include in terms      awareness, and efforts. They recognized
of cold and cough medicines, burn creams,         the significance of raising awareness and
and pain relievers, and others, in a simple,      exerting efforts towards their students. The
effective way that suits the target group. Some   remarkable joy and enthusiasm exhibited
medications that can be dispensed without a       by the children were duly acknowledged
physician’s prescription were also discussed      and celebrated. In a gesture of gratitude, the
(OTC medications), such as pain-relieving         school’s management presented certificates
and fever-reducing medications. Not only          to both the faculties’ staff and the students
was it limited to learning these topics, the      who actively participated in this enlightening
speakers were keen to make their message          visit, thus demonstrating their commitment
more effective by addressing another aspect,
                                                                       Vol. 2 - Issue 1 45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Chapter II

to community awareness. The university, in turn, deeply appreciates the dedication and initiative
shown by the students, and expresses its anticipation for further collaborations and community
involvements in the near future.

46 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Student Activities

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/MansouraNationalUniversity/posts/
pfbid0BjEBhxAoqbCa5nnV1ZcRopShNkgyLcsLz5mtZ5hbz5YMaB2yGFdMKNncQKDgj9T2l

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Chapter II

            Faculty Mentor Meeting

Faculty mentors play a crucial role in guiding and supporting students, offering academic

guidance as well as insights into personal and professional development. Beyond academics,
mentors help students develop essential skills like self-awareness, emotional intelligence, and
confidence through mentorship programs and one-on-one counseling.

Students express how transformative the guidance of their faculty mentors has been, empowering
them to step out of their comfort zones, get involved in extracurricular activities, and pursue
research projects.

Faculty of Pharmacy Mansoura National University recognizes the paramount importance of
these mentor-mentee relationships in cultivating a vibrant and supportive community that equips
students for success in their studies, careers, and beyond. The faculty mentorship program
is a shining example of the faculty’s dedication to providing a comprehensive and enriching
educational experience for its students.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/GTLWc7okJfy6HNDo/?mibextid=oFDknk

50 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Student Activities

                    Workshop On Time Management

Time management is a crucial skill that involves prioritizing tasks, setting goals, and efficiently

allocating your time to achieve those goals. It encompasses various techniques such as creating
to-do lists, prioritizing tasks based on importance and urgency, setting realistic deadlines, and
eliminating distractions. By mastering time management, you can enhance productivity, reduce
stress, and achieve a better work-life balance.
In the interest of Mansoura National University to provide academic support to its students,
The Faculty of Pharmacy at Mansoura National University, led by the SWH Team, organized
on Sunday, October 29th, 2023, a workshop entitled «Time Management» under the supervision
of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheikh, Assoc. Prof. Selwan El-Sayed, Dr. Heba Samir, Dr.Randa
Hani, and Dr.Basant Maher, during which the workshop focused on how to manage and organize
time before exams, highlighting the importance of developing this skill and providing practical
advice and strategies for students to make the most of their time during the study period and
avoid stress. Related topics were also discussed, such as setting study priorities, how to deal with
distraction and indulgence, as well as focusing on how to maintain mental health and achieve
balance between study and personal life.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/AdJsXjbdgJX2Sz78/?mibextid=oFDknk

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Chapter II

   Elevating The Academic Experience: Study Techniques For
               Semester Exams Workshop For Students

In a dedication to providing an exceptional educational journey for its students, Student Well-being

Hub at Pharmacy Mansoura National University has consistently demonstrated its unwavering
commitment to supporting its students through the organization of various events and initiatives.
The workshop, was introduced by Dr. Ahmed Hassan on the morning of Wednesday, November
29th, aimed to equip students with the necessary tools and strategies to excel during the upcoming
final exams of the first academic semester. The event featured a series of interactive sessions
designed to provide students with effective study techniques, foster positive engagement, and
offer practical strategies to manage their time and performance during the crucial examination
period.
By organizing this workshop, we focused on enhancing students’ study skills, promoting
effective time management, and fostering a positive mindset for the final exams that reaffirmed
our commitment to creating a supportive and enriching environment for our students, enabling
them to maximize their academic potential and achieve the greatest success in their educational
journeys.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/Cykea2fGRpA6M8t4/

52 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Student Activities

                      Enhancing Presentation Skills:
                 “How To Give A Bad Talk” Workshop

Recognizing the critical importance of effective communication and presentation skills in

the professional development of its students, the Faculty of Pharmacy at Mansoura National
University organized with the supervision of the SWH a thought-provoking workshop titled
“How to Give a Bad Talk” introduced by Dr. Randa Hani. This innovative approach to enhancing
public speaking abilities underscored the university’s commitment to empowering its aspiring
pharmacists with the essential skills needed to thrive in their future careers.
The workshop challenged students to explore the common pitfalls and mistakes often made
in academic and professional presentations, with the ultimate goal of equipping them with the
strategies and techniques to deliver impactful, engaging, and effective talks. Through a series
of interactive exercises, constructive feedback, and insightful discussions, students gained a
deeper understanding of the nuances of public speaking, from crafting compelling narratives and
utilizing visual aids effectively to managing stage presence and fostering audience engagement.
By intentionally addressing the obstacles and missteps that can hinder successful presentations,
the Faculty of Pharmacy provided its students with a unique learning opportunity to hone their
communication skills, bolstering their confidence and positioning them for success in their
academic pursuits and future professional endeavors. This innovative approach to professional
development exemplifies Mansoura National University’s dedication to producing well-rounded,
confident, and highly skilled graduates who are poised to make a lasting impact in the dynamic
field of pharmacy.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[MNU Pharmacy &
Entrepreneurship
Pioneering]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Chapter II

                     Global Entrepreneurship Week

On Monday, 20 November 2023, The Faculty of Pharmacy MNU
organized an awareness campaign regarding entrepreneurship,
which included the following:

“15 Steps to Become an Entrepreneur:”

1. Discovering Passion and Interest:
   It’s essential to pinpoint the field you’re passionate about
   and interested in. Try to select a domain that merges your
   interests and skills, and where you’re willing to devote your
   time and energy to excel.

2. Learning Essential Skills:
   Acquiring foundational knowledge and skills in
   entrepreneurship is crucial, encompassing areas like
   marketing, project management, and financial management.
   This can be attained through university courses or training
   programs.

3. Learning from Entrepreneurial Models:
   Gain insights from successful entrepreneurs and their stories
   of triumph. Understanding how they navigated challenges
   can be invaluable on your entrepreneurial journey.

4. Developing an Entrepreneurial Idea:
   Cultivate innovative ideas to address specific problems or
   fulfill market demands. Conduct thorough market research
   and gather data to refine your idea into a viable business
   concept.

5. Creating a Business Plan:
   Draft a comprehensive business plan and feasibility
   study outlining objectives, strategies, and requisite steps
   to materialize your idea. Include financial projections,
   marketing strategies, and operational plans, while considering
   contingency measures.

6. Seeking Funding:
   Secure funding for your venture by presenting your idea to
   potential investors or exploring startup support programs and
   competitions.

7. Experimenting and Learning:
   Embrace experimentation and extract lessons from hands-on
   experience. Anticipate challenges and setbacks, but remain
   resilient and learn from failures to enhance your project.

56 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Student Activities

8. Building a Strong Network:
   Forge connections with fellow entrepreneurs and experts in your field. Networking expands
   your knowledge base and opens up new opportunities.

9. Perseverance and Determination:
   Maintain unwavering determination and resilience amidst adversities. Acknowledge that
   entrepreneurship involves inevitable hurdles, but with perseverance, you can overcome them.

10. Communication and Marketing:
   Leverage social media and digital platforms to promote your idea and attract customers and
   partners.

11. Continued Learning and Development:
   Continuously upgrade your skills and knowledge through reading, workshops, and courses.
   Stay engaged with the entrepreneurial community.

12. Listening to Customers and Improving the Product or Service:
   Solicit and incorporate customer feedback to enhance your product or service. Customer
   satisfaction is paramount for rapid growth and sustained improvement.

13. Engaging with the Entrepreneurial Community:
   Participate in local and global entrepreneurial communities. Share experiences, insights, and
   learnings with peers in your field.

14. Readiness for Change and Adaptation:
   Acknowledge that entrepreneurship is an evolving journey. Be prepared to adjust your
   strategies in response to market shifts and make tough decisions.

15. Persistence and Resilience:
   Refuse to succumb to setbacks and challenges. Stay committed to your vision and persistently
   work toward your goals.

Remember, entrepreneurship is a journey filled with trials and triumphs. Embrace the process
and remain open to continuous learning and growth. While setbacks may arise, leveraging
experiences and resilience will ultimately pave the path to success.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=306074612250738&id=100085446049506

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Chapter II

     Let’s Unlock The Entrepreneurial Potential Within Our
  University And Empower The Next Wave Of Change Makers.

            An Entrepreneurial Universities Roundtable!

On 9th December, 2023, within the framework of developing the university’s strategic plan,
and under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater - University President, and the leadership of
Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheakh, an entrepreneurial roundtable was held focused on fostering
entrepreneurship and innovation in higher education aimed to bring together key stakeholders,
industry leaders, and passionate educators to strategize and shape the future of entrepreneurial
universities. Our primary goal was to facilitate collaborative discussions and generate innovative
ideas to enhance entrepreneurship education at Mansoura National University and beyond.
Added to:

   • Engage Stakeholders, as a diverse group of participants, including university representatives,
     entrepreneurs, industry experts, government officials, and students were invited and attended.
     This inclusive approach ensured a comprehensive range of perspectives and expertise.
   • Plan Engaging Sessions: The roundtable agenda comprised thought-provoking presentations,
     interactive panel discussions, and breakout sessions. Topics such as curriculum development,
     industry-academia collaborations, start-up incubation, and fostering an entrepreneurial mind-
     set among students were covered.
   • Promote Networking: The event provided ample opportunities for networking and relationship
     building, as we believe that forging connections among participants will lead to exciting
     collaborations and knowledge exchange beyond the roundtable itself.
   • Facilitate Action Planning: Through in-depth discussions, we aimed to develop an actionable
     roadmap for integrating entrepreneurship into the university’s curriculum, establishing
     support mechanisms for student start-ups, and fostering an entrepreneurial ecosystem on
     campus.
   • Drive Long-term Impact: The insights and outcomes from the roundtable will serve as
     a foundation for ongoing initiatives and policy changes to transform Mansoura National
     University into a hub for entrepreneurial education.
Together, we can shape the next generation of entrepreneurial leaders! Let’s unlock the
entrepreneurial potential within our university and empower the next wave of change makers.

58 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Student Activities

            Activities Of The First Forum For Qualifying
              Entrepreneurship Centers Ripple Summit

Pharmacy Mansoura National University ambassadors Made Waves at Ripple Summit, Elevating

our Brand on a Global Stage through an incredible opportunity to participate in the Ripple
Summit held at the Arab Academy for Science and Technology (AAST) on 18th December, 2023.
Our ambassadors showcased their knowledge, skills, and passion for innovation during this
prestigious event. They had the privilege to engage with some of the brightest minds in the field
and contribute to meaningful discussions surrounding the future of technology and its impact on
society.
The Ripple Summit at AAST provided a platform for exchanging groundbreaking ideas, fostering
collaboration, and exploring the endless possibilities of emerging technologies. Our ambassadors
actively participated in panel discussions, workshops, and interactive sessions, deepening their
understanding of cutting-edge advancements and trends in various fields.Their presence at
the summit not only represented our esteemed institution, but also highlighted the dedication
and expertise of our students. We are immensely proud of their achievements and the positive
impression they made on the international stage.We extend our heartfelt gratitude to the Arab
Academy for Science and Technology for hosting this remarkable event and providing a platform
for the exchange of knowledge and innovation.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Chapter II

               Empowering Pharmaceutical Innovators
  “Entrepreneurship In Pharmacy: Health Care Digitalization”

                                   Workshop

In its unwavering commitment to fostering a culture of innovation and entrepreneurship
among its students, the Faculty of Pharmacy at Mansoura National University recently hosted
a dynamic workshop titled “Entrepreneurship in Pharmacy: Health Care Digitalization” on 21st
November, 2023. This timely event underscored the faculty’s dedication to equipping its aspiring
pharmacists with the skills and knowledge necessary to navigate the rapidly evolving landscape
of the pharmaceutical industry.
The workshop provided a comprehensive exploration of the transformative role of digitalization
in the healthcare sector, highlighting the vast opportunities and challenges that pharmacists may
encounter as they navigate this dynamic field. Through a series of interactive sessions and expert-
led discussions, students were exposed to the latest trends, technologies, and business models
that are shaping the future of pharmaceutical care delivery. By empowering its students to think
beyond the traditional boundaries of the profession, the Faculty of Pharmacy demonstrated its
commitment to fostering a new generation of pharmaceutical innovators who are equipped to
lead the industry into the digital age. This forward-thinking approach not only enhances the
employability and entrepreneurial acumen of the university’s graduates but also positions
Mansoura National University as a trailblazer in the realm of pharmaceutical education, poised
to shape the future of the healthcare industry.

60 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Student Activities

     A Field Trip To Cairo International Technology Fair And
                             Innovation Forum

As part of its community engagement initiatives and in line with Mansoura National University’s
commitment to actively participating in major events that can benefit its students, develop their
skills, and expand their horizons in the fields of innovation and technology, a field visit to the
Cairo International Technology Fair and Innovation Form was held under the patronage of Prof.
Dr. Cherif Khater, the University President, the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh
Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the Faculty of Pharmacy, Dr. Walid Amir,
Dr. Randa Hany, Pharmacy Staff, and Mr. Hassan Abu Al-Wafa – Student Activities supervisor
at the University,
The primary objectives of this visit were to establish a strong network of relationships with the
entrepreneurs and startups present at the exhibition, learn about best practices in entrepreneurship,
and connect with a wide range of investors and supporting entities for nascent companies.
Mansoura National University’s participation in this prestigious event demonstrates its
commitment to fostering strong ties between the university and the local community, highlighting
its active role in serving society and developing the individual and collective skills of its students.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=313653848135038&id=100084712745066

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Our Faculty
New Insights]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Chapter II

       The University President’s Commitment To Academic
                                   Excellence

In a steadfast demonstration of his unwavering commitment to academic excellence, Prof. Dr.
Cherif Khater, the esteemed University President, convened a meeting on Tuesday, 21 November
2023, to closely monitor the educational progress and the administration of mid-term exams for
the first semester.
Recognizing the vital importance of maintaining the highest standards of academic rigor and
student success, President Khater gathered the university’s senior leadership, faculty, and
administrative teams to engage in a comprehensive review of the educational process. Through
open dialogue and a data-driven analysis of student performance indicators, the meeting delved
into the challenges and opportunities inherent in the mid-term examination period, with the goal
of identifying areas for targeted support and continuous improvement. By fostering a culture of
transparency, accountability, and collaborative problem-solving, President Khater’s leadership
has been instrumental in ensuring that Mansoura National University remains at the forefront of
academic excellence, empowering its students to reach new heights of achievement.

64 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Student Activities

        Scientific Trip To EPICO Pharmaceutical Company

Under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, University President, and the leadership of

Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh – Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at
the faculty of Pharmacy, and supervision of Dr. Randa Hani and Dr. Amgad Salem, the MNU
College of Pharmacy organized a scientific trip to “Epico Pharmaceutical Company” on Tuesday,
November 28, 2023. The visit aimed to enrich the students’ knowledge and expand their horizons
in the field of the pharmaceutical industry, introduce them to the different departments in
factories, and learn about the different areas of job opportunities for pharmacists in factories and
companies. The visit began with a welcome and a speech by the company’s representatives, then
a presentation on the history and founding of the company and the most important medicines that
are manufactured, as well as the importance of the pharmaceutical industry. A tour was conducted
inside the factory to learn about the different and modern stages of drug manufacturing and to
see up close the most precise processes of manufacturing and preparing it for its arrival on the
market.
EIPICO is one of the leading companies in the pharmaceutical market in Egypt and the Arab
world. The company manufactures more than 400 pharmaceutical preparations covering 25
therapeutic groups, including antibiotics, freeze-dried products, and Spansol capsules.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 65]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Chapter II

            Let’s Renew Our Energies

Under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, University President, and the leadership of Assoc.
Prof. Ahmed R. Al-Sheikh, Director of the PharmD Clinical Pharmacy Program at the Faculty
of Pharmacy, and the supervision of Dr. Yomna Al-Laithi, a cultural and recreational trip was
organized by the Faculty of Pharmacy to Alexandria city on the morning of Thursday, November
30th, in collaboration with the Student Activities Sector. During the trip, students explored the
various landmarks of the city. The aim was to motivate students to regain their vitality, encourage
them to continue their academic pursuit actively, and enhance a comprehensive balance between
academic and recreational aspects in students’ lives. It’s worth mentioning that the trip was
supervised by Mr. Hassan Abu El-Wafa, the head of student activities at the university, Ms.
Amani Al-Imbabi, the general manager of the university headquarters, Dr. Kareem El-Maadawi,
the head of the student affairs at the faculty, and Ms. Iman Hossam, the procurement specialist
at the university.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/VpzevSEdEFLj9ihh/?mibextid=xfxF2i

66 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Student Activities

     Celebrating The Selfless Spirit Of Student Volunteers At
               Pharmacy Mansoura National University

On the occasion of International Volunteer Day, the esteemed administration of the Faculty of

Pharmacy at Mansoura National University extends its heartfelt gratitude and sincere appreciation
to the dedicated student volunteers who have selflessly contributed to various fields of volunteer
work.
These exceptional individuals have demonstrated an unwavering commitment to serving their
community, from organizing impactful events and campaigns to actively participating in scientific
activities and recreational initiatives. Their tireless efforts have not only enriched the lives of
their fellow students but have also fostered a culture of solidarity, empathy, and community
participation within the Faculty of Pharmacy.
The Faculty of Pharmacy takes great pride in recognizing the invaluable contributions of its
second-year student volunteers. We extend our heartfelt wishes for their continued success and
express our fervent hope that their shining example will inspire others to follow in their footsteps.
Through the power of volunteerism, these students have not only enriched their own personal
development but have also played a vital role in uplifting the reputation and impact of Mansoura
National University on the local and global stage.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 67]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Chapter II

      Unveiling The Unseen: Rare Diseases Exhibition Shines
    A Light At Pharmacy Mansoura National University’s 1st

                      Student Pharmacy Conference

Mansoura National University’s Faculty of Pharmacy is proud to host an exceptional exhibition
on the sidelines of its 1st Student Conference in the Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology.
This awe-inspiring showcase aimed to spread awareness about rare diseases and the extraordinary
challenges faced by those living with them.
The exhibition featured a powerful collection of thought-provoking posters that delved into the
intricacies of rare diseases. These conditions, often with limited understanding and treatment
options, have a profound impact on the lives of patients and their families. By bringing these
posters to the forefront, the Faculty of Pharmacy seeks to raise awareness, foster empathy, and
encourage further research and support for rare diseases.
Each poster told a unique and compelling story, highlighting the resilience, strength, and
determination of those facing rare diseases. Exhibition’s Attendees had the opportunity to
engage with these posters, learning about the complexities of rare diseases and gaining a deeper
understanding of the courageous individuals who navigate these extraordinary circumstances.
Through this remarkable exhibition, the Faculty of Pharmacy hopes to drive positive change and
rally the community towards a future where rare diseases are better understood, diagnosed, and
supported. By shining a light on the unseen, we can work together to make a lasting difference
in the lives of those affected by rare diseases.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/SNLEsJoaNZADn8MC/

68 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[Student Activities

       Empowering Students Through Academic Advising At
       Mansoura National University’s Faculty Of Pharmacy

As a leading institution in the field of pharmaceutical education, Mansoura National University’s

Faculty of Pharmacy has consistently demonstrated its unwavering commitment to the academic
and personal growth of its students. At the core of this commitment lies the faculty’s robust
academic advising program, which plays a pivotal role in guiding and supporting students
throughout their educational journey.
The academic advising services offered by the Faculty of Pharmacy are designed to provide
students with personalized guidance and mentorship, enabling them to navigate the complexities
of their academic path with confidence and clarity. Helmed by a dedicated team of experienced
faculty staff, the advising program ensures that each student receives tailored support, from
course selection and academic planning to career exploration and personal development. By
fostering meaningful and ongoing dialogues with their advisors, students are empowered to
make informed decisions, overcome challenges, and ultimately achieve their educational and
professional aspirations. This holistic approach to academic advising underscores the Faculty of
Pharmacy’s dedication to cultivating well-rounded, successful, and confident graduates who are
poised to make a lasting impact in the field of pharmaceutical sciences.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=285786104279589&set=pcb.285786624279537

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 69]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[Chapter II

      Empowering Pharmacy Students Through Educational
                             Pharmacy Training

At the Mansoura National University Faculty of Pharmacy, the commitment to empowering
students extends far beyond the classroom walls. The faculty has established a robust training
program that provides students with hands-on, practical experiences to complement their academic
studies, ultimately preparing them for successful careers in the dynamic field of pharmacy.
The faculty’s Educational Pharmacy training approach is designed to offer students a well-
rounded and immersive learning experience. Students were given the opportunity to work with
prescriptions, dispense OTC medications, and organizing the community pharmacy. All these
skills were held by Dr. Amged Salem under the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheahk
at the Educational pharmacy at the MNU Pharmacy that simulates the real world practice.
By integrating this comprehensive training, the Mansoura National University Faculty of Pharmacy
ensures that its graduates are not only academically proficient but also possess the practical
expertise and problem-solving abilities required to thrive in the ever-evolving pharmaceutical
landscape. This holistic approach to education not only enhances the employability of the
faculty’s students but also positions them as leaders and innovators within the industry, ready to
make a lasting impact on patient care and the advancement of the pharmaceutical sciences.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=296165926550497&set=pcb.296166076550482

70 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[Student Activities

          Celebrating The World Future Day At Mansoura
               National University Faculty Of Pharmacy

In a spirit of innovation and forward-thinking, the Mansoura National University Faculty of

Pharmacy recently celebrated the World Future Day, a global initiative that aims to inspire and
empower individuals to envision and shape the future. The celebration of World Future Day at the
Mansoura National University Faculty of Pharmacy not only inspired students to think critically
about the future but also reinforced the faculty’s commitment to staying at the forefront of the
ever-evolving field of pharmacy. By actively engaging with the latest trends and technologies, the
faculty is ensuring that its students are well-equipped to navigate the challenges and capitalize
on the opportunities that the future holds, ultimately positioning them as the next generation of
pharmaceutical leaders and innovators.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=312966401561559&set=a.108292155362319

  Fostering Artistic Expression: Mansoura National University
        Faculty Of Pharmacy Hosts Student Art Exhibition

In a continuous effort to nurture and showcase the creative talents of its students, the Mansoura

National University Faculty of Pharmacy recently organized a student art exhibition, providing
a platform for budding artists to share their artistic expressions.
The exhibition, which was held at the faculty’s premises, featured a diverse array of captivating
works, including paintings, drawings, sculptures, and mixed-media creations. The displayed
artworks reflected the students’ unique perspectives, showcasing their innate creativity and
artistic abilities.
The successful hosting of the student art exhibition underscores the faculty’s commitment
to nurturing a well-rounded educational experience, one that recognizes the importance of
cultivating both academic and creative excellence. By empowering its students to express
themselves through the arts, the Faculty of Pharmacy is not only fostering personal development
but also enriching the cultural landscape of the university and the surrounding community.

   Installation Of E-Stock Pharmacy Software For Pharmacy
                                 Management

In order to train students in all fields and disciplines in the labor market and in line with keeping

pace with everything new in the fields of work, the e-Stock Pharmacy program for pharmacy
management has been installed on computers in the college in order to help students keep pace
with the practical pharmacy practices to qualify them practically.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/permalink.php?story_
fbid=pfbid02o55NFVQKQewJFLgUc56zWTpmJwfr6q212L8kPrEs5WyZnjz26vtuibywWdmXJAZnl&id=100085446049506

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 71]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Chapter III

Galleries

at MNU Faculty of Pharmacy]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Abstract

We are thrilled to share our new galleries at
MNU Faculty of Pharmacy. These innovative
spaces represent a significant milestone in our
commitment to the development of our students
and the advancement of pharmaceutical
education. The power of these new galleries
lies in their ability to provide a dynamic and
immersive learning environment, fostering
hands-on experiences and promoting active
engagement among students. Our galleries
offer an opportunity for students to explore the
world of pharmacy through interactive exhibits,
practical demonstrations, and collaborative
learning experiences. We firmly believe that
these new galleries will have a profound impact
on our students, enabling them to develop a
deeper understanding of the pharmaceutical
field and equipping them with the skills and
knowledge necessary for their future careers.]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[Chapter III

             Pharmacy MNU Organic Chemistry Gallery

The Organic Chemistry Gallery in the Faculty of Pharmacy plays a crucial role in the education

of pharmacy students. Organic chemistry is the branch of chemistry that deals with the structure,
properties, composition, reactions, and synthesis of organic compounds. In the context of
pharmacy, organic chemistry is essential for understanding the structure and function of drugs
and their interactions with the human body. The Organic Chemistry Gallery provides a space
where students can explore organic molecules, chemical reactions, and reaction mechanisms
through interactive displays, molecular models, and laboratory demonstrations. This hands-on
learning experience helps students develop a solid foundation in organic chemistry, enabling
them to understand drug design, drug synthesis, and drug metabolism. The gallery serves as a
hub for students to engage with the fundamental concepts of organic chemistry, fostering their
critical thinking and problem-solving skills in the context of pharmaceutical science.

74 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[Galleries

    Pharmacy MNU Physiology and Pathophysiology Gallery

The Physiology and Pathophysiology Gallery in the Faculty of Pharmacy is of great importance

for students studying pharmacy. Having a dedicated gallery for Physiology and Pathophysiology
allows students to visually understand the mechanisms underlying various diseases and their
impact on different organ systems. The gallery displayed anatomical models, interactive
diagrams, and multimedia presentations that help students grasp complex concepts and make
connections between pathophysiology and pharmacotherapy. By observing and studying these
visual aids, students can develop a deeper understanding of disease processes, which is crucial
for their future roles as pharmacists. The gallery provides a valuable learning environment that
enhances students’ knowledge and prepares them to provide effective healthcare interventions.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 75]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

Honoring And

Outstanding Staff

And Students

                                                               Honoring and acknowledging university
                                                               staff and students is crucial as it recognizes
                                                               their valuable contributions. University staff,
                                                               including professors and support personnel,
                                                               creates a positive learning environment and
                                                               helps students succeed. Recognizing staff
                                                               through appreciation events and awards boosts
                                                               morale and fosters motivation. Similarly,
                                                               honoring students for their achievements
                                                               promotes a culture of excellence and inspires
                                                               others. Acknowledging their efforts validates
                                                               their hard work and fosters a supportive and
                                                               inclusive community.]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities
                    Of The Biochemistry Course

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif        Best Biorender design award:
Khater - President of the University, and         Mohamed Bondok
the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed              Mohamed Gomaa
R. El-Sheakh - Director of the Pharm D            Mohamed Hesham
Program at the Faculty of Pharmacy, and           Mohamed Saed
the supervision of Assoc. Prof. Yousra El-        Mohamed Maghawry
Far, and as part of the Faculty of Pharmacy,      Mohamed Elgohary
Mansoura National University’s pioneering         Karim Ashraf
efforts in the field of pharmaceutical            Fares Salah
sciences, and as a commitment from the            Osama Elshazly
university to develop its students’ practical     Omar Elganiny
and innovative skills and to motivate them to
practice self-learning utilizing advanced and  Most creative poster award:
professional tools, the students of the 2nd       Abeer Al-Alfy
level designed and presented posters with the     Amany Ali
aid of BioRender under the following theme:       Rehab Hatem
“Genetic Horizons: Unveiling the Future of        Salma Mohamed
Biochemical Discoveries”.                         Doha ALi
                                                  Shahd Roshdy
 What was special about the Biochemistry          Shahd Ramadan
poster day that the graphics used in each         Shahd M. Ramadan
poster ware self-designed and created by the      Amal Abdo
students through web based tools. Assoc.          Safa Magdi
Prof. Ahmed Ramadan & Assoc. Prof.
Youssra El-far granted the students four       Most presentable team award:
awards including:                              Bioinformatics Poster
                                               The honoring ceremony was coordinated by
Best poster design award:                      biochemistry staff members Ass. Lec. Yomna
                                               Elleithi, Ph. Shereen Elnabawy, and Ph. Iman
   Esraa Wajeh                                 Manar Elislam. The event was also delighted
                                               with the presence of pioneering biochemistry
   Amira Mosaad                                personnel Assoc. Prof. Noha Mansour &
                                               Assoc. Prof. Randa Zaghlol.
   Rahma Nasef

   Shorouq M. Anwar

   Raghda Anwar

   Zeinb Moataz

   Aya Ahmed

   Asmaa Bahnasy

   Razan Mohamed

   Eman Ayman

   Samar Magdy

78 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=337433275781538&set=pcb.337434519114747

                                                                              Vol. 2 - Issue 1 79]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

         Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational
                  Activities Of The Biostatistics Course

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif
Khater, University President, and the
leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-
Sheakh, Director of the Pharm D Program
(Clinical Pharmacy), and the supervision
of Dr. Bassant Maher, Dr. Karim Saad, Dr.
Ahmed Hassan, Dr. Abdul Rahman Emara
We celebrated by honoring the best students
and groups participating in the scientific
day for Biostatistics”Discovering the art of
Biostatistics in Research”. The primary focus
of the activity was to apply the knowledge
acquired in the biostatistics course to real-
world research papers. Students engaged
in reading, interpreting, navigating, and
presenting internationally published research
papers, thereby demonstrating a remarkable
level of commitment, dedication, and
enthusiasm.
The rewards were categorized as the
following:
Top 3 Presenters

   1. Muhammad Hamdi Al-Alfi
   2. Renad Wael Fathi
   3. Muhammad Yasser Al-Azab

Best Teams
   Groups 7 – 10 – 11 – 13 – 19

Team Work Support
   Group 18

80 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/100085446049506/videos/715629267368485

                                                                 Vol. 2 - Issue 1 81]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational Activities
     Of The Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry Course

As a part of improving the quality of education     Salma Kamal Fahmy
and keeping up with modern developments,            Salma Mohamed Abdel Azim
Mansoura National University is keen on             Salma Mohammad Hamid	
providing an educational environment                Salma Mahmoud Al-Husseiny
that encourages students to explore ideas        Team 4
and analyze information more deeply by              Basmala Al-Haj Hassan
integrating research and innovation methods         Basmala Tariq Addel Azim
into teaching styles. Under the patronage of        Basmala Abdel Maqsoud
Prof. Dr. Cherif Khater, University President,      Basmala Nasser Shuhbor
and the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R.         Basmala Bassem Soroor
Al-Sheakh, Director of the Pharm D Program          Basant Ahmed Abo Al-Majd
(Clinical Pharmacy), Prof. Dr. Jenny Jehan,         Nourhan Nasser Shahbor
and Dr. Heba Samir with the supervision of       Team 5
Dr. Shimaa Mostafa, Dr. Walaa Nabil, Dr.           Rana Sabry Mahmoud.
Diaa Dagher, and Dr. Mohammed Othman,              Rana Mohamad Al-Sharaidi
we honored students who dedicated the best         Rana Gharib Mohamed
demands in the Pharmaceutical Analytical           Rana Mohamrd Abu Al-Anin
Chemistry activities and the rewards were          Rana Fahmy Abdel Aziz
categorized as the following:                      Rana Mosaad Atef
                                                 Team 6
Top 10 (Presentation):                             Shadi Mohamed Semary
                                                   Shahinaz Fayez Abd Elsamie
Team 1                                             Shahinaz Hany Morad
                                                   Shaza Ahmed Abdel-Aleem
   Omnia Abdel Sattar                              Shorouk Yasser Fathy
                                                   Sherif Mohamed Ghareeb
   Omnia Mohamed Kamal                           Team 7
                                                   Aamaa Mohamed Ali
  Amir Nabil Ahmed                                 Eman Saber Salah
                                                   Ibrahim Ahmed Mohamed
  Amira El-Sayed Mahmoud                           Ibrahim Ayman Mostafa
                                                   Ibrahim Hassan Ali
  Amira Alaa Fathi	

  Amira Ai Ahmed

Team 2

   Farah Amgad Mustafa

   Farah Sherif Fathi

   Karim Ahmed Sharaf El-Din

   Karim Reda Al-Shahat

   Karim Sabry Fekry Ahmed

Team 3

   Salma Hassan Ahmed

   Salma Tarek Mohamad

82 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

  Ibrahim Mohamed Ibrahim
  Sherif Mohamed Ghareeb
Team 8
   Basmala Al-Haj Hassan
   Basmala Tariq Addel Azim
   Basmala Abdel Maqsoud
   Basmala Nasser Shuhbor
   Basmala Bassem Soroor
   Basant Ahmed Abo Al-Majd
   Nourhan Nasser Shahbor
Team 9
  Ayatallah Ibrahim Al-Desouki
  Aya Mohamed Rizq
  Ayatallah Mohamed Ramah
  Aya Mohamed Abo-Taleb
  Aya Hamda Zain Al-Abidin
  Arwa Hatem Mohamed
Team 10
  Heba Ahmed Fadel
  Heba Walid Ramzi
  Heba Shaaban Mahmoud
  Hadeer Magdy Ahmed
  Heba Mohamed Hafez
  Hana Hamada Hamed

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/GN7MxRq5zvJDFdzy/?mibextid=oFDknk

                                                                    Vol. 2 - Issue 1 83]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

    Celebrating Excellent Students In The Educational
Activities Of The Physiology & Pathophysiology Course

Under the patronage of Prof. Dr. Cherif          Top 3 Posters
Khater, University President, and the            Team 1
leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed R. Al-
Sheakh, Assoc. Prof. Marwa Zaghlol, and             Raghad Kandil Fathi
supervision of Dr. Yomna Ashraf, Dr. Karim          Aseel Mohammed Elsayed
Saad, Dr. Ahmed Hassan, Dr. Rana Gamal, we          Esraa Nasser Mahmoud
celebrated by honoring the best students and        Sara Mohamed Mansour
groups for their activities in the Physiology &     Bassant Hamza Sabry
Pathophysiology aligned with the 1st Student     Team 2
Conference at the Faculty of Pharmacy,              Nada Abo-elella Hassan
Mansoura National University, that brought          Maha Ahmed Ahmed
the fascinating world of 3D models and              Noha Samy Mohammed
posters to the forefront of exploration.            Tasneem Zamil Mustafa
                                                    Nourhan Mohamed Ahmed
The rewards were categorized as the              Team 3
following:                                          Shorouq Mohamed Eltelbany
                                                    Amira Mosaad Abo Elftouh
Top 3 (3D Model)                                    Esraa Wajeeh Kamal
                                                    Rahma Nasef Kamel
Team 1                                              Razan Mohamed Elmergawy

   Yousef Mohamed Yousef                         The Best Creative Poster
                                                    Shahd Mohamed Ramadan
   Abdalla Emad Shehata                             Amany Ali Esmail
                                                    Aber Elalfy Ramadan
   Abdelrahman Mahmoud Dawod                        Shahd Ramadan Abdelkarem
                                                    Doha Ali Abdelaleem
   Ahmed Hesham Nageb                               Doha Ali Abdelaleem

   Ahmed Sameh Mohamed

Team 2

  Shahd Elsayed Gwily

  Hana Tarek Khodair

  Dina Mahmoud Mohammed

  Soha Tharwat Elaseed

Team 3

  Ahmed Sultan Hamid

  Ahmed Nashaat Mohamed

  Ahmed Mahmoud Abdo

  Omar Reda Mohamed

  Ali Mohamed

84 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

           Vol. 2 - Issue 1 85]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

     Let’s Celebrate Our Top Students In The First Semester
                                   2023/2024

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=345017308356468&set=a.108292155362319
https://www.facebook.com/photo/?fbid=344962235028642&set=a.108292155362319

86 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

Let’s Celebrate Our Top Students In The Second Semester
                               2023/2024

                                                            Vol. 2 - Issue 1 87]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

                      College’s First Excellence Day

In an effort from Mansoura National University to honor the efforts made by the faculty
members, the supporting staff, and the university’s administrative staff, and to enhance the spirit
of motivation and encouragement to achieve more successes, and under the patronage of Prof.
Cherif Khater, President of the University, and the leadership of Assoc. Prof. Ahmed Al-Sheakh,
Director of the Pharm D Program – Clinical Pharmacy at the College of Pharmacy.
On the morning of Tuesday, January 30, 2024, the College of Pharmacy organized the college’s
first Excellence Day, during which it presented the achievements during the first semester in the
academic field and student activities, and the required aspects of excellence and improvement.
Participants from the faculty members, including academic staff, administrative staff, as well
as Exemplary Employees and Technicians, were all honored for their efforts in completing the
educational process throughout the semester.

The Outstanding Professional Teaching Awards were introduced to:

• Dr. Yehia Amin						• Dr. Samar Samir

• Dr. Noha Mansour						           • Dr. Yousra El-Far

• Dr. Bassant Maher						          • Dr. Abdelrahman Emara

• Dr. Manar Monir						            • Dr. Diaa Dagher

• Dr. Abdullah Haikal						• Dr. Ahmed Hassan

• Dr. Kareem Saad						            • Dr. Mayye Majed

• Dr. Aya Abu El Fadl						        • Dr. Yomna El-Lithi

The Outstanding Performance in Monitoring & Evaluation Awards were introduced to:

• Dr. Walid amir

• Dr. Abdelrahman Emara

• Dr. Mohamed Othman	

88 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

The Flora of Medicinal Plant of Mansoura National University educational website Medical
Terminology Wiki project, and the Regulation – FDA Expedition were awarded

                     the top three educational projects at the college for this year.
The Best Scientific Department Award were ranked as the following:
1st Place: Pharmacognosy department.
2nd Place: Clinical Pharmacy & Pharmacy Practice department.
3rd Place: Physiology and Pathophysiology department.
Physiology & Pathophysiology and Medical Terminology courses received Best Platform.
The Pharmacognosy course received the highest student surveys. The Physiology and
Pathophysiology (Level II) and Mathematics & Biostatistics (Level I) courses received Best
Textbook, and the. In the field of community participation and survey committee (Dr. Randa
Hhanie), also Top 3 Task Mystery (Dr. Walid amir, Dr. Abdelrahman Emar, and Dr. Mayye
Majed), Best performance in QAU (Dr. Noha Mansour and Dr. Randa Hani), best administrative
staff; Mr. Air Philip and Mohamed Abuelfadl, were also honoured.

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 89]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[Chapter IV

90 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[Honoring and outstanding

The ceremony is considered a motivating motivation to achieve the highest levels of performance,
and to embody the College’s vision and mission of leadership and excellence, in addition to
enhancing the interactive spirit and active participation in the process of achieving excellence
and academic excellence. The college administration extends its thanks and appreciation to all its
employees, the university administration, and its employees for the continuous support.

Reference:

https://www.facebook.com/share/p/KPBy9XvrxWkZg3Xr/?mibextid=qi2Omg

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 91]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[Chapter V

Meet Our Staff’s Recent

Research Publications]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[Abstract

	 It is with great pleasure that we invite
you to join us in celebrating some of our staff’s
publications in last few months. The publication
of the research article represents a significant
milestone in our academic and professional
careers, and we believe it is a testament to the
hard work and dedication of the entire research
team. Additionally, we would be delighted to
have you join us on our specific occasion which
is publishing a research article affiliated with
the Faculty of Pharmacy - Mansoura National
University for the first time in its inaugural year.]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[Chapter V

Nilotinib Alleviates Paraquat-Induced Hepatic And Pulmonary
Injury In Rats Via The Nrf2/Nf-Kb Axis

        International Immunopharmacology. 2023 Nov; 124(Pt A): 110886.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

           Azza R Elkholy 1 , Ahmed R El-Sheakh 1, 2, 3 , Ghada M Suddek 1

1 Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt.
2 Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura National University, Gamasa,

  Egypt.
3 Future studies and Risks management’ National Committee of Drugs, Academy of Scientific Research, Ministry of

  Higher Education, Elsayeda Zeinab, Egypt.

Abstract

Background: Paraquat (PQ, 1,1′-dimethyl-4-4′-bipyridinium dichloride) is a highly toxic
quaternary ammonium herbicide widely used in agriculture. It exerts its toxic effects mainly
as a result of its redox cycle via the production of superoxide anions in organisms, leading to
an imbalance in the redox state of the cell causing oxidative damage and finally cell death. The
aim of this study was to estimate the beneficial protective role of nilotinib (NIL) on PQ-induced
hepatic and pulmonary toxicity in rats.
Methods: Male wistar rats were randomly divided into four groups, namely control, PQ (15 mg/
kg), PQ plus NIL (5 mg/kg) and PQ plus NIL (10 mg/kg). NIL (5 and 10 mg/kg/day) was taken
by oral syringe for five days followed by a single intra-peritoneal administration of PQ (15 mg/
kg) on sixth day.
Results: Pretreatment with NIL relieved the histological damage in liver and lung tissues
and improved hepatic biochemical markers. It significantly (p < 0.05) reduced serum levels
of ALT, AST, ALP, Y-GT and total bilirubin while increased that of albumin. Meanwhile, NIL
significantly (p < 0.05) reduced oxidative stress markers via reduction of malondialdhyde (MDA)
and elevation of glutathione (GSH) contents in liver and lung tissues. In addition, it significantly
(p < 0.05) decreased the inflammation by reducing hepatic and pulmonary tumor necrosis factor
alpha (TNF-α) and nuclear transcription factor kappa B (NF-KB/p65) contents. Nilotinib also
down-regulated apoptosis by reducing cysteinyl aspartate-specific proteinase-3 (caspase-3).
Furthermore, it upregulated the expression of nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2)
and microtubule-associated protein 1A/1B-light chain 3 II (LC3II) in liver and lung tissues.
Significance: NIL suppressed PQ-induced inflammation, oxidative stress and apoptosis in liver
and lung tissues by modulating Nrf2/Nf-kB axis.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intimp.2023.110886

94 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[Research Publications

The Clinical Outcomes Of Dapagliflozin In Patients With Acute Heart
Failure: A Randomized Controlled Trial (Dapa-Response-Ahf)

            European Journal Of Pharmacology. 2023 Dec; 961: 176179.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Abdelrahman N Emara 1, Moheb Wadie 2, Noha O Mansour 1,3, Mohamed E E Shams 1

1 Clinical Pharmacy and Pharmacy Practice Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura University, Mansoura,
  35516, Egypt.

2 Cardiology Department, Faculty of Medicine, Mansoura University, Mansoura, 35516, Egypt.
3 Clinical Pharmacy and Pharmacy Practice Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura National University,

  Egypt.

Abstract

Aims: Dapagliflozin may confer additional decongestive and natriuretic benefits to patients with
acute heart failure (AHF). Nonetheless, this hypothesis was not clinically examined. This study
aimed primarily to investigate the effect of dapagliflozin on symptomatic relief in those patients.
Methods: This was a randomized, double-blind study that included 87 patients with AHF
presenting with dyspnea. Within 24 h of admission, patients were randomized to receive either
dapagliflozin (10 mg/day, N = 45) or placebo (N = 42) for 30 days. The primary outcome was the
difference between the two groups in the area under the curve (AUC) of visual analogue scale
(VAS) dyspnea score over the first 4 days. Secondary endpoints included urinary sodium (Na)
after 2 h of randomization, percent change in NT-proBNP, cumulative urine output (UOP), and
differences in mortality and hospital readmission rates.
Results: The results showed that dapagliflozin significantly reduced the AUC of VAS dyspnea
score compared to placebo (3192.2 ± 1631.9 mm × h vs 4713.1 ± 1714.9 mm × h, P < 0.001).
The relative change of NT-proBNP compared to its baseline was also larger with dapagliflozin
(-34.89% vs -10.085%, P = 0.001).Additionally, higher cumulative UOP was found at day 4 (18600
ml in dapagliflozin vs 13700 in placebo, P = 0.031). Dapagliflozin decreased rehospitalization
rates within 30 days after discharge, while it did not affect the spot urinary Na concentration,
incidence of worsening of heart failure, or mortality rates.
Conclusion: Dapagliflozin may provide symptomatic relief and improve diuresis in patients
with AHF. Further studies are needed to confirm these findings.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2023.176179

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 95]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[Chapter V

A Multinational Study On The Factors Influencing University
Students’ Attitudes And Usage Of Chatgpt

                        Scientific Reports. 2024 Jan; 14(1): 1983.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 Maram Abdaljaleel, Muna Barakat, Mariam Alsanafi, Nesreen A Salim, Husam
 Abazid, Diana Malaeb, Ali Haider Mohammed, Bassam Abdul Rasool Hassan,
Abdulrasool M Wayyes, Sinan Subhi Farhan, Sami El Khatib, Mohamad Rahal,
Ali Sahban, Doaa H Abdelaziz, Noha O Mansour 1,2 , Reem Alzayer, Roaa Khalil,
        Feten Fekih-Romdhane, Rabih Hallit, Souheil Hallit, Malik Sallam

1 Clinical Pharmacy and Pharmacy Practice Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura University, Mansoura
  35516, Egypt. 19 Clinical.

2 Pharmacy and Pharmacy Practice Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura National University, Dakahlia
  Governorate 7723730, Egypt.

Abstract

Artificial intelligence models, like ChatGPT, have the potential to revolutionize higher education
when implemented properly. This study aimed to investigate the factors influencing university
students’ attitudes and usage of ChatGPT in Arab countries. The survey instrument “TAME-
ChatGPT” was administered to 2240 participants from Iraq, Kuwait, Egypt, Lebanon, and
Jordan. Of those, 46.8% heard of ChatGPT, and 52.6% used it before the study. The results
indicated that a positive attitude and usage of ChatGPT were determined by factors like ease
of use, positive attitude towards technology, social influence, perceived usefulness, behavioral/
cognitive influences, low perceived risks, and low anxiety. Confirmatory factor analysis indicated
the adequacy of the “TAME-ChatGPT” constructs. Multivariate analysis demonstrated that the
attitude towards ChatGPT usage was significantly influenced by country of residence, age,
university type, and recent academic performance. This study validated “TAME-ChatGPT” as a
useful tool for assessing ChatGPT adoption among university students. The successful integration
of ChatGPT in higher education relies on the perceived ease of use, perceived usefulness, positive
attitude towards technology, social influence, behavioral/cognitive elements, low anxiety, and
minimal perceived risks. Policies for ChatGPT adoption in higher education should be tailored
to individual contexts, considering the variations in student attitudes observed in this study.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-024-52549-8.

96 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Comparative Novel Green Reversed-Phase High-Performance
Liquid Chromatography Method ForSimultaneous Determination
Of Ivabradine And Carvedilol In Tablets And Human Plasma
Using Uv And Fluorescence Detectors

               Sustainable Chemistry And Pharmacy. 2024; 38: 101476.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 Ethar A. Rashad 1, Samar S. Elsayed 1, Jenny Jeehan M. Nasr 1, 2, Fawzia A. Ibrahim 1

1 Department of Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura University, Mansoura,
  35516, Egypt.

2 Department of Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, Mansoura National University,
  Gamasa, 7731168, Egypt.

Abstract

A rapid, green, and sensitive dual detection technique method was applied using both UV and
fluorimetric detection to determine ivabradine and carvedilol in their pure form, combined tablet
formulation, and in the spiked human plasma. The method was achieved by using HyperClone™
MOS C8 column (150 × 4.6 mm, with particle size 5 μm), and a mixture composed of
(70:10:20%v/v) ethanol: methanol: 0.02 M potassium phosphate buffer adjusted to pH = 3 b
y using o-phosphoric acid. The dual detection technique was performed at 210 nm in the case
of UV detection, and at 337 nm after excitation at 282 nm in the case of fluorimetric detection
with a flow rate of 1 mL/min. The retention time in the proposed method was found to be 2.13
and 4.72 min for carvedilol and ivabradine respectively (UV detection) and 2.16 and 4.5 min for
carvedilol and ivabradine respectively (fluorescence detection). It was found to be a rectilinear
method (r > 0.999), precise (RSD <2 %), and accurate (recoveries 99.92 and 100.52). The method
was simple, specific, sensitive, and robust. Calibration graphs were found to be rectilinear
from 0.25 to 11.25 μg/mL and 0.50–16 μg/mL for carvedilol and ivabradine for UV detection,
while from 30 to 210 ng/mL and 48–400 ng/mL for carvedilol and ivabradine for fluorimetric
detection. A correlation coefficient (r) was 0.9999 for the two drugs in UV and fluorimetric
detection approaches. Fixed–dose combination tablets containing both medications could be
examined routinely by the validated method without interference from excipients. Moreover,
the fluorimetric detection HPLC technique can be applied to determine the studied drugs in the
human plasma with high accuracy and precision. Greenness of the method was assessed by using
Eco-scale and AGREE metrics, and the method was found to be green.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scp.2024.101476

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 97]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[Chapter V

Efficacy Of Montelukast As An Adjuvant Therapy In Rheumatoid
Arthritis Patients: A Randomized Controlled Study

         International Immunopharmacology, 2023 Nov; 124(Pt B):110959.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Basma M Ahmed , Noha O Mansour , Rehab A Sallam , Moetaza M Soliman

Abstract

Objective: This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of montelukast in conjunction with non-
biologic disease modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (nDMARDs) in rheumatoid arthritis (RA)
patients.
Methods: This study was a single-center randomized double-blinded placebo-controlled study.
Adult RA patients were included if they had moderate to severe disease activity and were receiving
monotherapy or combination of nDMARDs. Eligible patients were randomized, in 1:1 ratio, to
receive either 10 mg montelukast or placebo, once daily for 16 weeks. The primary endpoint
was the change in the 28-joints disease activity score (DAS28) 16 weeks after treatment. The
patients’ quality of life (QoL) was assessed by the Arabic version of the Health Assessment
Questionnaire-Disability Index. Moreover, serum levels of vascular adhesion molecule-1
(VCAM-1) were measured.
Results: A total of 87 patients completed the study; 44 in the montelukast arm and 43 in the control
arm. After 16 weeks of treatment, disease activity decreased significantly in the montelukast arm
with mean change in DAS28 (95% CIs) of −1.5 (−1.7, −1.2) while the control arm showed no
improvement (0.2 (0.0, 0.4), p < 0.01). The QoL of the patients improved significantly from
baseline in the montelukast arm (p < 0.01) but not in the control arm (p = 0.08). The median
(IQR) serum levels of VCAM-1 were significantly lower in the montelukast arm (22.8 (15.0–
32.7)) than in the control arm (28.9 (15.4–42.8), p = 0.004).
Conclusion: The co-administration of montelukast with nDMARDs in RA patients enhanced the
anti-rheumatic effect which was reflected clinically by decreased disease activity.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intimp.2023.110959

98 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Evaluation Of Knowledge, Experiences, And Fear Toward
Prescribing And Dispensing Corticosteroids Among Egyptian
Healthcare Professionals: A Cross-Sectional Study

              Saudi Pharmaceutical Journal. 2023 Oct; 31(10): 101777.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Muna Barakat, Noha O Mansour , Mohamed Hassan Elnaem, Samar Thiab, Rana Abu

                   Farha, Malik Sallam, Ahmed Said Ali, Doaa H Abdelaziz

Abstract

Background: Corticosteroids (CS) are essential drugs in the treatment of several medical
conditions. Assuming different roles, physicians and pharmacists play a primary role in
prescribing and dispensing these medications to optimize patients’ clinical management. The
data on assessing knowledge and experience of healthcare professionals toward CS is scarce.
Therefore, this study aimed to assess and compare knowledge, experience, and fears towards CS
among Egyptian physicians and pharmacists.
Methods: A cross-sectional, self-administrated, validated online questionnaire was used to collect
the data from Egyptian healthcare professionals. The questionnaire consisted of four sections with
multiple choice questions: sociodemographic (7 questions), knowledge about CS (13 questions),
experience with CS prescription/dispensing (5 questions), and fears and preferences toward CS
prescription/dispensing (13 questions). Descriptive and inferential statistics were used to analyze
the data.
Results: A total of 600 responses were analyzed in this study. The study sample was almost two-
half of healthcare providers: 303 (50.5%) pharmacists and 297 (49.5%) physicians. Pharmacists
had marginally higher knowledge scores as compared to those recorded for physicians (11.29
versus 10.16, respectively; P = 0.047). Physicians had more experience choosing corticosteroids
in treatment plans based on their experience (51.8% vs 38.5%) and guideline recommendations
(72.8% vs 50.9%) than pharmacists. However, pharmacists had more experience dealing with
corticosteroid use based on patients’ preferences (19.5% vs 4.9%) and showed a broader scope of
experiencing side effects of corticosteroids with their patients. The two professions demonstrated
high levels of fear, with pharmacists acknowledging significantly lower concerns about CS than
physicians (3.72 versus 4.0, respectively; P = 0.003).
Conclusion: Discrepancies exist among healthcare professionals in knowledge and experience,
favoring better scientific knowledge of pharmacists related to corticosteroids. Based on these
findings, the interprofessional collaborative efforts would provide comprehensive, patient-
centered care that maximizes the benefits of CS while minimizing their risks.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsps.2023.101777

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 99]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[Chapter V

 Salutary Influence Of Gemifloxacin Mesylate Nanocubosomes
 Based-In Situ Ocular Gel As A Novel Approach For The
 Management Of Experimental Keratitis Induced By Mrsa

      Journal Of Drug Delivery Science And Technology. 2023 Nov; 89: 105012.
          ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

   Ghada Ahmed El-Emam, Amira Motawea, Walaa Ibrahim Abd El Hady, Sameh
            Saber, Ahmed A.e.mourad, Heba A. Ramadan, Ahmed M. El-Baz

 Abstract

  In the era of Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) resulting in the ineffectiveness
  of antibiotics is of keen interest to researchers in up-to-date scenarios. The current study aims
  to formulate water-soluble drug (Gemifloxacin) loaded nanocubosomes via melt dispersion
  emulsification method using glyceryl mono oleate/poloxamer 407 in different ratios. Firstly,
  the optimized formula (F6) was evaluated for surface morphology, particle size, polydispersity
  index, zeta potential, drug entrapment efficiency%, compatibility studies, and in vitro release.
  Secondly, the optimized formulation of nanocubosomes was laden as in situ gel and evaluated
  for gelling effect, in vitro release, drug content, stability study, and antimicrobial activity. The
  optimized nanocubosomes F6 showed a particle size of less than 200 nm, a zeta potential −26.6
  ± 1.3 mV, and a high entrapment efficiency of 96.62 ± 2.35%. The developed in situ gel (F6)
  shows prolonged drug release and good stability. Our objectives in that study are to investigate
  the effectiveness of that novel approach for the management of corneal lesions and inflammation
  in a rat model of MRSA keratitis as well as in vitro estimation for their MIC. Results showed
  greater potency by having lower MICs than Gemifloxacin solution and significant reductions
  in corneal opacity and inflammation score in rats treated with GEM-loaded nanocubosomes
  compared to those treated with Gemifloxacin solution. Histopathological analysis demonstrated
  a preservation of the normal corneal structure in the GEM-loaded nanocubosomes group. It is
  clear from the above-performed studies that the prepared in situ gel would afford a profitable
  treatment for keratitis with a lack of irritancy.

 Reference:

  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jddst.2023.105012

100 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Investigating Fluorogenic Labelling Of Amine Coupled With
First-Order Derivative Spectrofluorimetry As A Versatile
Analytical Methodology: Application To Estimation Of
Benoxinate In Its Eye Drops

  Spectrochimica Acta Part A: Molecular And Biomolecular Spectroscopy. 2024
                                      Jan 15:305:123410.

        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
     Rasha Aboshabana , Heba Samir Elama , Heba Elmansi , Samah Abo El Abass

Abstract

In this research, fluorogenic labelling followed by applying first-order derivative spectrofluorimetry
for the developed fluorophore is discussed as an alternative, sensitive and selective analytical
approach. Benoxinate, containing a primary amine and fluorescamine reagent were selected for
the study. Then the proposed methodology relies on the reaction between the primary amine in
benoxinate with fluorescamine that selectively reacts with primary amines to develop highly
fluorescent products. The fluorescamine-benoxinate developed fluorophore is identified by its
sharp first-order derivative peak at 465 nm following excitation at 386 nm in borate buffer,
pH 8. The optimum reaction conditions were ascertained. Following ICH validation guidelines,
the first order derivative of the relative fluorescence intensity for the developed fluorophore
was linearly related to benoxinate concentration and ranged from 20.0 to 200.0 ng/mL with
a detection limit of 3.36 ng/mL and a quantitation limit of 10.19 ng/mL, moreover, satisfying
accuracy and precision values were obtained upon statistical analysis of results. The offered
analytical method was successfully applied to quantify benoxinate in raw material and Benox®
eye drops as a direct application to a commercial formulation.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.saa.2023.123410

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 101]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[Chapter V

 Formulation Of Lipid Polymer Hybrid Nanoparticles Of The
 Phytochemical Fisetin And Its In Vivo Assessment Against
 Severe Acute Pancreatitis

                         Scientific Reports. 2023 Nov; 13(1): 19110.
          ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Randa Hanie Awadeen , Mariza Fouad Boughdady , Randa A Zaghloul, Wael M

            Elsaed, Irhan Ibrahim Abu Hashim, Mahasen Mohamed Meshali

 Abstract

  Fisetin (FST) is a naturally occurring flavonol that has recently emerged as a bioactive
  phytochemical with an impressive array of biological activities. To the author knowledge,
  boosting the activity of FST against severe acute pancreatitis (SAP) through a nanostructured
  delivery system (Nanophytomedicine) has not been achieved before. Thereupon, FST-loaded
  lipid polymer hybrid nanoparticles (FST-loaded LPHNPs) were prepared through conjoined
  ultrasonication and double emulsion (w/o/w) techniques. Comprehensive in vitro and in vivo
  evaluations were conducted. The optimized nanoparticle formula displayed a high entrapment
  efficiency % of 61.76 ± 1.254%, high loading capacity % of 32.18 ± 0.734, low particle size
  of 125.39 ± 0.924 nm, low particle size distribution of 0.357 ± 0.012, high zeta potential of +
  30.16 ± 1.416 mV, and high mucoadhesive strength of 35.64 ± 0.548%. In addition, it exhibited
  a sustained in vitro release pattern of FST. In the in vivo study, oral pre-treatment of FST-
  loaded LPHNPs protected against L-arginine induced SAP and multiple organ injuries in rats
  compared to both FST alone and plain LPHNPs, as well as the untreated group, proven by both
  biochemical studies, that included both amylase and lipase activities, and histochemical studies
  of pancreas, liver, kidney and lungs. Therefore, the study could conclude the potential efficacy
  of the novel phytopharmaceutical delivery system of FST as a prophylactic regimen for SAP and
  consequently, associated multiple organ injuries.

 Reference:

  https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-46215-8.

102 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Inhibition Of Colorectal Cancer Targets Il-6, Ctla-4, & B7-2 By
Tislelizumab: Molecular Docking, Dynamics, & String Protein-
Protein Network Analysis

                 Informatics In Medicine Unlocked. 2023; 41: 101323.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Mahmoud Elkazzaz, Shahid Ullah, Tianshun Gao, Israa M. Shamkh, Amr Ahmed,
    Ted X. Wu G, Maii S. Elsharayidi, Mohammad Shahbaz Khan, Aziz-Ur Rehman,

                 Marwa M. Lotfy, Abdullah Haikal, Mahmoud Abdalrahman

Abstract

As a DNA mismatch repair deficit (dMMR) anticancer medication, and a humanized monoclonal
antibody (hmAb), Tislelizumab has attracted significant interest in recent years. The programmed
cell death protein-1 (PD-1) and its ligands (PD-L1/CD274/B7-H1 and PDL2/CD273) may
bind to each other with great affinity. This binding prevents activated T-cells from continuing
to proliferate, produce cytokines, and engage in cytotoxic action. The B7:PD-1 inhibitory
immunological checkpoint receptor binds to the B7-2(CD86) B-lymphocyte activation antigen.
This paper presents Tislelizumab’s molecular docking and dynamics simulations with the
receptor B7-2(CD86) and its downstream signaling proteins CTLA-4 and IL-6. When docked
to B cell stimulatory factor-2 soluble IL-6 receptor alpha (sIL6Ra/CD126), Tislelizumab had
a strong binding affinity of 329 kcal/mol and provided an excellent quality model with an
LGscore of 4.54. The type I membrane protein B7-2(CD86), a member of the immunoglobulin
superfamily, responded to docking with an affinity of −332.35 kcal/mol and LGscore of 2.54.
Docking to the immune checkpoint protein receptor cytotoxic T-lymphocyte-associated protein-4
(CTLA-4/CD152) had a binding affinity of −305.91 kcal/mol, facilitating immunological
control and cellular dissociation. Tislelizumab and these target proteins exhibited persistent
and advantageous interactions in molecular dynamics studies. The STRING functional protein-
protein network analysis supported our in silico docking and dynamic simulation results. This
analysis also included comparisons of the binding modes of mAbs to protein receptors involved
in the cancer hallmark mechanism(s), demonstrating that IL-6, B7-2, and CTLA-4 act and are
inhibited in group-mode. Functional enrichment analysis and molecular modelling supported
the relationship between the hallmarks of the tumor microenvironment that link inflammation to
immunity. Tislelizumab may therefore be able to prevent these three proteins from acting. These
findings may also shine light on Dostarlimab’s mode of action, which in 2022 achieved ground-
breaking success in a clinical study for colorectal cancer.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/
j.imu.2023.101323

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 103]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[Chapter V

Ai-Driven Discovery Of Celecoxib And Dexamethasone For

Exploring Their Mode Of Action As Human Interleukin
(Il-6) Inhibitors To Treat Covid-19-Induced Cytokine Storm In

Humans

Current Pharmaceutical Design. 2023 Oct; 29(34): 2752 – 2762.

------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

Israa M. Shamkh , Mahmoud Elkazzaz, Enas. S. Radwan, Jawayria Najeeb, Md.

Tabish Rehman , Mohamed F. Alajmi, Moayad Shahwan, Muhammad Sufyan,

Nouf Khalifa Alaqeel, Ibrahim A. Ibrahim, Basit Jabbar, Mohammad Shahbaz

Khan, Tomasz M. Karpiński, Abdullah Haikal, Reem M. Aljowaie, Saeedah

Abstract   Musaed Almutairi, Amr Ahmed

Background: In the case of COVID-19 patients, it has been observed that the immune system
of the infected person exhibits an extreme inflammatory response known as cytokine release
syndrome (CRS) where the inflammatory cytokines are swiftly produced in quite large amounts
in response to infective stimuli. Numerous case studies of COVID-19 patients with severe
symptoms have documented the presence of higher plasma concentrations of human interleukin-6
(IL-6), which suggests that IL-6 is a crucial factor in the pathophysiology of the disease. In order
to prevent CRS in COVID-19 patients, the drugs that can exhibit binding interactions with IL-6
and block the signaling pathways to decrease the IL-6 activity may be repurposed.

Methods: This research work focused on molecular docking-based screening of the drugs
celecoxib (CXB) and dexamethasone (DME) to explore their potential to interact with the
binding sites of IL-6 protein and reduce the hyper-activation of IL-6 in the infected personnel.

Results: Both of the drugs were observed to bind with the IL-6 (IL-6 receptor alpha chain) and
IL-6Rα receptor with the respective affinities of -7.3 kcal/mol and -6.3 kcal/mol, respectively,
for CXB and DME. Moreover, various types of binding interactions of the drugs with the target
proteins were also observed in the docking studies. The dynamic behaviors of IL-6/IL-6Rα in
complex with the drugs were also explored through molecular dynamics simulation analysis.
The results indicated significant stabilities of the acquired drug-protein complexes up to 100 ns.

Conclusion: The findings of this study have suggested the potential of the drugs studied to be
utilized as antagonists for countering CRS in COVID-19 ailment. This study presents the studied
drugs as promising candidates both for the clinical and pre-clinical treatment of COVID-19.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.2174/0113816128260449231017091824

104 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Bioactivity Of Eriocephalus Africanus Essential Oil Against
Concanavalin A-Induced Hepatitis Via Suppressing Immune
Cell Infiltration, Inhibiting Tnf-Α/Nf-Κb And Ifn-Γ/Stat1
Signaling Pathways

           Journal Of Ethnopharmacology. 2024 Jan; 318(Pt B): 117000.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Abdullah Haikal , Amal A Galala, Mahmoud Elshal, Yhiya Amen, Ahmed A Gohar

Abstract

Ethnopharmacological relevance: Eriocephalus africanus infusion is used as a diuretic and
a diaphoretic and is also used in the treatment of gastrointestinal disorders and gynaecological
conditions, inflammation and dermal disorders, asthma, coughs, fevers, and painful ailments.
The plant has been used traditionally as a medication to cure inflammation and skin problems.
Aim of the study: Studying E. africanus essential oil (EAEO) as a potential hepatoprotective
measure against concanavalin (Con) A-induced hepatitis in mice and investigating its underlying
mechanism.
Materials and methods: Hydro-distilled oil of the fresh plant aerial shoots is subjected to GC/
MS analysis. Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) was induced in mice by intravenous injection of Con
A (15 mg/kg). EAEO was administered orally before Con A injection to test its hepatoprotective
activity.
Results: GC/MS analysis revealed the presence of 22 compounds representing 99.43% of the oil
components. The monoterpene artemisia ketone (41.02%) and the sesquiterpene juniper camphor
(14.17%) are the major components. The in vivo study showed that the oil suppressed Con
A-induced neutrophil and CD4+T cell infiltration into the liver, restored hepatic redox balance,
inhibited Con A-induced elevation of tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α), interleukin (IL-6),
and interferon-gamma (IFN-γ) hepatic levels which were correlated with its ability to suppress
nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) and Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription (STAT1)
activation in the liver.
Conclusion: EAEO showed hepatoprotective potential against Con A-induced hepatitis in mice
collectively through selective anti-oxidant, anti-inflammatory, and anti-necrotic effects.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2023.117000

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 105]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[Chapter V

  Multi-Targeted Anti-Alzheimer’s Agents: Synthesis, Biological
  Evaluation, And Molecular Modeling Study Of Some
  Pyrazolopyridine Hybrids

          European Journal Of Medicinal Chemistry. 2023 Dec; 262: 115880.
          ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
    Omnia M Waly , Selwan M El-Sayed , Mariam A Ghaly, Hussein I El-Subbagh

  Abstract

  A new series of compounds bearing a pyrazolopyridine scaffold was synthesized as integrated
  anti-Alzheimer’s disease (AD) multi-targeted ligands. Compounds 49 and 51 showed remarkable
  activity as hAChE inhibitors with IC50 values of 0.17 and 0.16 μM, respectively; and proved to
  be active hBuChE inhibitors with IC50 values 0.17 and 0.69 μM, eight and two-fold more active
  than the reference compound rivastigmine, respectively. Compounds 49 and 51 showed potent
  GSK3β inhibition with IC50 values of 0.21 and 0.26 μM, respectively compared to L807mts.
  Also, 49 and 51 showed 66.0 and 60.0% as tau protein aggregation inhibitors; and Aβ1-42 self-
  aggregation inhibitors with 79.0 and 75.0% respectively. Furthermore, 49 and 51 could bind
  virtually with the PAS affecting Aβ aggregation, thus preventing Aβ-dependent neurotoxicity.
  They proved to have the ability to chelate bio-metals such as Fe2+, Cu2+, and Zn2+ preventing
  their oxidative damage in the brain of AD patients, in addition to their safety upon WI-38 cell line.
  Both compounds could virtually penetrate BBB and obeyed Lipinski’s rule of five. Compounds
  49 and 51 could be considered as MTDLs for AD patients and the obtained model and pattern
  of substitution could be used for further development of new multi-targeted anti-Alzheimer’s
  agents.

  Reference:

   https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2023.115880

106 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[Research Publications

New 2-Alkoxycyanopyridine Derivatives As Inhibitors Of
Egfr, Her2, And Dhfr: Synthesis, Anticancer Evaluation, And
Molecular Modeling Studies

            Bioorganic And Medicinal Chemistry. 2023 Dec; 141: 106874.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Samia S Hawas , Selwan M El-Sayed, Perihan A Elzahhar, Mohamed A Moustafa

Abstract

New series of substituted 2-alkoxycyanopyridine derivatives were synthesized and evaluated for
their in vitro and in vivo anticancer activities. Comparing the evaluated activities against cancer
cell lines to the broad-spectrum anticancer doxorubicin, and the kinase inhibitor sorafenib,
compounds 3a, 4b, 4c, 7a, and 8d demonstrated superior anticancer efficacy with elevated safety
profiles and selectivity indices, particularly against MCF7 breast cancer. For exploration of their
mechanism of action, assays for inhibition of EGFR, HER2 kinase, and DHFR were performed.
The promising synthesized compounds exhibited potent dual kinase EGFR/HER2 inhibitory
activity with IC50 values of 0.248/0.156 μM for 4b and 0.138/0.092 μM for 4c. Additionally,
with IC50 values of 0.138 and 0.193 M, respectively, 4b and 4c had the greatest DHFR inhibitory
activity that was comparable to methotrexate. In the MCF7 breast cancer cell line, they caused
arrest at the S phase of the cell cycle and exhibited apoptosis induction activity. With restored
caspase-3 immunoexpression, the anti-breast cancer assay performed in vivo of 4b and 4c
demonstrated a substantial decrease in tumor volume. Results from molecular modeling were in
agreement with biological assays proving the importance of the 3-caynopyridine, two substituted
phenyl rings attached to central pyridine ring, and propoxy side chain moieties for binding with
the receptors. As 4c works by inhibiting both EGFR/HER2 kinase, DHFR enzymes, in addition
to cellular apoptosis, it could be viewed as a model of compounds possessing a multi-targeting
anticancer activity. Collectively, compounds 4b and 4c might represent prototypes for further
development as anticancer molecules.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2023.106874

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 107]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[Chapter V

  Tetraenone A: A New Β-Ionone Derivative From Tetraena
  Aegyptia

                                 Metabolites. 2023; 13(12): 1202.
          ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
     Ahmed Ashour, Asmaa E. Sherif, Selwan M El-Sayed, Ji-Young Kim, Dae Sik
     Jang, Abtin Anvari, Abdelbasset A. Farahat, Sabrin R. M. Ibrahim, Gamal A.
    Mohamed, Bayan E. Ainousah, Raghad F. Aljohani, Razan R. Al-Hejaili, Rahaf

                        H. Khoja, Ahmed H. E. Hassan, Ahmed A. Zaki

  Abstract

  In this study, the chemical investigation of Tetraena aegyptia (Zygophyllaceae) led to the
  identification of a new megastigmene derivative, tetraenone A ((2S, 5R, 6R, 7E)-2-hydroxy-
  5,6-dihydro-β-ionone) (1), along with (3S, 5R, 6S, 7E)-3-hydroxy-5,6-epoxy-5,6-dihydro-β-
  ionone- (2), 3,4-dihydroxy-cinnamyl alcohol-4-glucoside (3), 3β,19α-dihydroxy-ursan-28-oic
  acid (4), quinovic acid (5), p-coumaric acid (6), and ferulic acid (7), for the first time. The
  chemical structures of 1–7 were confirmed by analysis of their 1D and 2D NMR and HRESIMS
  spectra and by their comparison with the relevant literature. The absolute configurations of 1
  and 2 were assigned based on NOESY interactions and ECD spectra. Conformational analysis
  showed that 1 existed exclusively in one of the two theoretically possible chair conformers with
  a predominant s-trans configuration for the 3-oxobut-1-en-1-yl group with the ring, while the
  half-chair conformer had a pseudo-axial hydroxy group that was predominant over the other
  half-chair conformation. Boat conformations were not among the most stable conformations,
  and the s-trans isomerism was in favor of s-cis configuration. In silico investigation revealed
  that 1 and 2 had more favorable binding interactions with Mpro rather than with TMPRSS2.
  Accordingly, molecular dynamic simulations were performed on the complexes of compounds
  1 and 2 with Mpro to explore the stability of their interaction with the target protein structure.
  Compounds 1 and 2 might offer a possible starting point for developing covalent inhibitors of
  Mpro of SARS-CoV-2

  Reference:

   https://doi.org/10.3390/metabo13121202

108 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Repurposing Synthetic Congeners Of A Natural Product Aurone
Unveils A Lead Antitumor Agent Inhibiting Folded P-Loop
Conformation Of Met Receptor Tyrosine Kinase

                           Pharmaceuticals. 2023; 16(11): 1597.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
  Ahmed H. E. Hassan, Cai Yi Wang, Cheol Jung Lee, Hye Rim Jeon, Yeonwoo Choi,
Suyeon Moon, Chae Hyeon Lee, Yeon Ju Kim, Soo Bin Cho, Kazem Mahmoud, Selwan

                           M El-Sayed, Sang Kook Lee, Yong Sup Lee

Abstract

A library of 24 congeners of the natural product sulfuretin were evaluated against nine panels
representing nine cancer diseases. While sulfuretin elicited very weak activities at 10 µM
concentration, congener 1t was identified as a potential compound triggering growth inhibition
of diverse cell lines. Mechanistic studies in HCT116 colon cancer cells revealed that congener
1t dose-dependently increased levels of cleaved-caspases 8 and 9 and cleaved-PARP, while it
concentration-dependently decreased levels of CDK4, CDK6, Cdc25A, and Cyclin D and E
resulting in induction of cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in colon cancer HCT116 cells. Mechanistic
study also presented MET receptor tyrosine kinase as the molecular target mediating the anticancer
activity of compound 1t in HCT116 cells. In silico study predicted folded p-loop conformation
as the form of MET receptor tyrosine kinase responsible for binding of compound 1t. Together,
the current study presents compound 1t as an interesting anticancer lead for further development.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.3390/ph16111597

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 109]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[Chapter V

  Design, Synthesis, And Repurposing Of Rosmarinic Acid-Β-
  Amino-Α-Ketoamide Hybrids As Antileishmanial Agents

                             Pharmaceuticals. 2023; 16(11): 1594.
          ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
   Ahmed H.e. Hassan, Waleed A. Bayoumi, Selwan M El-Sayed, Trong-Nhat Phan,
    Taegeun Oh, Gyeongpyo Ham, Kazem Mahmoud, Joo Hwan No, Yong Sup Lee

  Abstract

  A series of rosmarinic acid-β-amino-α-ketoamide hybrids were synthesized and rationally
  repurposed towards the identification of new antileishmanial hit compounds. Two hybrids, 2g
  and 2h, showed promising activity (IC50 values of 9.5 and 8.8 μM against Leishmania donovani
  promastigotes, respectively). Their activities were comparable to erufosine. In addition,
  cytotoxicity evaluation employing human THP-1 cells revealed that the two hybrids 2g and
  2h possess no cytotoxic effects up to 100 µM, while erufosine possessed cytotoxicity with
  CC50 value of 19.4 µM. In silico docking provided insights into structure–activity relationship
  emphasizing the importance of the aliphatic chain at the α-carbon of the cinnamoyl carbonyl
  group establishing favorable binding interactions with LdCALP and LARG in both hybrids 2g
  and 2h. In light of these findings, hybrids 2g and 2h are suggested as potential safe antileishmanial
  hit compounds for further development of anti-leishmanial agents.

  Reference:

   https://doi.org/10.3390/ph16111594

110 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[Research Publications

Design, Synthesis, In Vitro, And In Silico Studies Of New N5-
Substituted-Pyrazolo[3,4-D]Pyrimidinone Derivatives As
Anticancer Cdk2 Inhibitors

                           Pharmaceuticals. 2023; 16(11): 1593.
        ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 Waheed A. Zaki, Selwan M El-Sayed, Mohamed Alswah, Ahmed El-Morsy, Ashraf H.
Bayoumi, Abrahman S. Mayhoub, Walaa H. Moustafa, Aeshah A. Awaji, Eun Joo Roh,

                              Ahmed H.e. Hassan, Kazem Mahmoud

Abstract

CDK2 is a key player in cell cycle processes. It has a crucial role in the progression of various
cancers. Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and colorectal cancer (CRC) are two common cancers
that affect humans worldwide. The available therapeutic options suffer from many drawbacks
including high toxicity and decreased specificity. Therefore, there is a need for more effective
and safer therapeutic agents. A series of new pyrazolo[3,4-d]pyrimidine analogs was designed,
synthesized, and evaluated as anticancer agents against the CRC and HCC cells, HCT116, and
HepG2, respectively. Pyrazolo[3,4-d]pyrimidinone derivatives bearing N5-2-(4-halophenyl)
acetamide substituents were identified as the most potent amongst evaluated compounds. Further
evaluation of CDK2 kinase inhibition of two potential cytotoxic compounds 4a and 4b confirmed
their CDK2 inhibitory activity. Compound 4a was more potent than the reference roscovitine
regarding the CDK2 inhibitory activity (IC50 values: 0.21 and 0.25 µM, respectively). In
silico molecular docking provided insights into the molecular interactions of compounds 4a
and 4b with important amino acids within the ATP-binding site of CDK2 (Ile10, Leu83, and
Leu134). Overall, compounds 4a and 4b were identified as interesting CDK2 inhibitors eliciting
antiproliferative activity against the CRC and HCC cells, HCT116 and HepG2, respectively, for
future further investigations and development.

Reference:

https://doi.org/10.3390/ph16111593

                                                               Vol. 2 - Issue 1 111]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[Acknowledgment                      Leadership and innovation in pharmaceutical
                                    education, training, scientific research, and community
  VISION                            service within the framework of sustainable
                                    development to reach a prominent position regionally
                                    and internationally in the field of pharmacy.

MISION                              Our goal is to prepare qualified pharmacists regionally
                                    and internationally, following the latest scientific and
                                    professional standards that are commensurate with the
                                    needs of the labor market and the scientific community.
                                    We aim to instill the values and ethics of the pharmacy
                                    profession while enabling our graduates to compete
                                    and keep pace with scientific and technological
                                    developments to raise the efficiency of the treatment
                                    system and achieve sustainable growth.

STRATEGIC                           1- Supporting and developing the education, learning,
GOALS                                  and student support system.

                                    2- Developing the capabilities of the college’s human
                                       resources from faculty members, assistant staff,
                                       technicians, and administrative staff.

                                    3- Preparing distinguished graduates who can compete,
                                       link them to the college, and meet the needs of
                                       the labor market while supporting the goals of
                                       sustainable development.

                                    4- Maximizing community participation and building
                                       local and international partnerships.

                                    5- Establishing an applied scientific research system
                                       and constantly strengthening it.

                                    6-Sustaining the infrastructure and developing the
                                       college’s resources.

112 Faculty of Pharmacy Newsletter]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[Editorial Board                                          Editorial Board

                 Editor in Chief
                    Assoc.Prof. Ahmed R. El-Sheakh

                 Editor
                    Dr. Bassant Maher

                 Graphic Design
                    Hamada Hamdy

                 Revised by
                    Dr. Selwan Mahmoud
                    Dr. Eman Manar El-Eslam

                 Editorial Assistants, PSA Students
                    Rehab Ehab
                    Salma Mohammed
                    Gehad Safwat
                    Nada Elkatry
                    Rawan Mostafa
                    Salma Eslam
                    Nada Sameh
                    Esraa Wajeeh
                    Habiba Hani
                    Mariam Maher
                    Ahmed Ghazy
                    Ahmed Elsebaey

                                                 Vol. 2 - Issue 1 113]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[Thank You]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[Faculty Of Ph                                                         armacy Mansoura National University

                  ‫ ﺟﺎﻣـﻌـﺔ ﺍﻟﻤﻨﺼـﻮﺭﺓ ﺍﻷﻫﻠﻴـﺔ‬- ‫ﻛﻠﻴـﺔ ﺍﻟﺼﻴــﺪﻟـﺔ‬

                             FACULTY OF PHARMACY - MANSOURA NATIONAL UNIVERSITY

‫ ﻣﺤﺎﻓﻈﺔ ﺍﻟﺪﻗﻬﻠﻴﺔ‬- ‫ ﻣﺪﻳﻨﺔ ﺟﻤﺼﺔ‬- ‫ ﻣﺎﻳﻮ‬15 ‫ ﻣﻨﻄﻘﺔ‬- ‫ﺍﻟﻄﺮﻳﻖ ﺍﻟﺪﻭﻟﻲ ﺍﻟﺴﺎﺣﻠﻲ‬

International Coastal Road - 15th of May District - Gamasa City - Dakahlia Governorate
                                   phdclinical@mansnu.edu.eg]]></page></pages></Search>